<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ravi Kumar Pillai</title>
    <description>Author, Coach, Mentor and Consultant</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 20:31:09 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 28 Jun 2020 20:31:09 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Anatomy of Intolerance</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Peacock is the National Bird of India. Known for its exquisite charm and peaceful demeanor, the bird radiates a synergy with nature. However, the typical Indian social behavior seems more aligned to the ostrich than to peacock. We bury our heads in sand and pretend not to see our own faults, prejudices and biases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Intolerance is seemingly deep routed in our social psyche. Most people consider it quite normal to hate, spread lies, prejudge, typecast and exclude those with different lifestyles, habits, thinking and beliefs. Look around and listen to the hush voices of frustration and alienation in the air. Wake up to the reality of the walls that we have been busy building. Intolerance manifests in innumerable ways in our way of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Few years back, I was appointed as the Managing Director of a Government of Kerala enterprise upon my selection through a transparent process. I had come from the corporate sector and my education, belief system and experience probably positioned me as a rank outsider to the setting. There were couple of IAS officials in the Board of the company. When I found that they abstained from Board Meetings, I inquired with the Corporate Secretary about possible reasons. I was told that as ‘privileged’ civil servants, they did not as a convention attend Board Meetings when the Chief Executive was not one of their own tribe. I do not know, whether the culture has changed &lt;em&gt;now. It was a crude encounter for me with bureaucratic intolerance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Compared to the crass intolerance that ordinary citizens face day in and day out, my experience was nothing to write home about.&lt;/em&gt; In office, academic institutions and most formal set ups, we come across behaviors involving open and oblique clannishness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We seem to be a classificatory society; we look for reasons to organize into exclusive clusters within the larger social space. Alumni of colleges, coming from a locality, belonging to certain communities, based on political leanings, trade union affinities …… the list of fragmented identities is endless. We feel more at ease belonging to the part than to the whole!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;When it gets into the social domain, the classificatory culture gets nastier.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the example of Aslam. As a newly appointed officer in a nationalised bank, Aslam arrives at one of the highly polarised cities in India and seeks to settle down into an established housing society. He might simply be refused the opportunity because his religion or eating habits are not aligned to majority of the occupants in the community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Bengaluru, it is common to see young techies frantically running around for housing because landlords are typically reluctant to rent out to bachelors, more so to single women.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In films, sports, business and official domains, gender insensitivities are rampant.&lt;/strong&gt; I remember once we were boarding a plane and as the welcome announcement came from the lady captain, the gentleman next to me in his safari suite and with a mouthful of pan masala exclaimed, &lt;em&gt;“Pilot Aurat hai kya? Hamen to dar lagta hai?”&lt;/em&gt; Misogyny, caste biases and regional prejudices are among the most common forms of intolerance in the Indian society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you think intolerance is restricted to geographies with relatively low Human Development Index, you are mistaken. We recently heard a senior politician in Kerala making a loaded comment on the international compliments received by the State Health Minister for her stellar performance in combating the Covid challenges. I could only mumble, “ Old habits hesitate to die down”!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it is the continuing story of &lt;em&gt;racial prejudices against migrants from the North East&lt;/em&gt;, ugly manifestations of &lt;em&gt;caste-based marginalization&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;prejudices against minorities&lt;/em&gt;, exclusionary &lt;em&gt;attitudes to LGBT&lt;/em&gt; community or &lt;em&gt;linguistic and regional bigotry&lt;/em&gt;, intolerance is widely practiced in the world’s largest democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Political intolerance&lt;/strong&gt; is a virus that gets protection and encouragement by parties of various hues. &lt;em&gt;Grass root workers and mercenaries of parties take intolerance to the level of physical violence.&lt;/em&gt; Stories of political violence from certain pockets in Northern Kerala have been making headlines for all the wrong reasons, till a few months back. How many youths in our schools and colleges had to sacrifice their lives in mindless clashes in and around campuses?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Emotional intolerance&lt;/strong&gt; is even more virulent and contagious than physical intolerance. Bullying, harassment, blocking normal and deserved progress in career and professions are woven into the contemporary culture in India. Marital discords, violence to spouses and neglect of the elderly are manifestation of emotional intolerance. Blatant selfishness and an ill-placed sense of entitlement based on ‘status’(or &lt;em&gt;self-importance&lt;/em&gt;) drive intolerance to a pathological obsession. Though intolerance drives the target population to distress and alienation, it also displays the lack of self-confidence of the protagonists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bertrand Russell, the archetypal role model of free thinking spoke of the biases in society, &lt;strong&gt;“Collective fear stimulates herd instinct, and tends to produce ferocity toward those who are not regarded as members of the herd.”&lt;/strong&gt; Doesn’t this ring a bell in the instances mob lynching, honour killing and caste atrocities that keep happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The rural landscape of India, especially in traditional societies is replete with instances of harassment and punitive brutality at the hands of the village councils and the archaic &lt;em&gt;‘khap’&lt;/em&gt; (community) panchayats. These are manifestations of gross social injustice perpetrated with acquiescence, and often connivance, of the powers that be. &lt;em&gt;Caste is at the root of our culture of intolerance. It is an anachronism in the current times and the social stratification based on caste is nothing short of apartheid.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of all intolerances, &lt;strong&gt;intellectual intolerance is the most orchestrated and manipulated type.&lt;/strong&gt; The feigned and harvested sectarian intolerance is indeed fodder to the self-seeking politicians. Any one who stands for free thinking and critical inquiry can be branded as an outlier, anti-national or urban Naxalite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at the fuss we make about a book, movie or play that depicts a view point not aligned to the conservative narrative. If you ban, condemn or boycott an idea it is natural that mere curiosity would draw many people to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;How do we deal with the entrenched virus of intolerance in our society?&lt;/strong&gt; We have ignored it, swept it under the carpet and tolerated it for too long. The virus of intolerance is indeed a cancer on the social fabric and it feeds on the emotions and sensibilities of citizens. It undergoes dangerous mutations impacting the way we perceive, relate to and support each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mother Teresa said in plain and simple words, &lt;em&gt;“If you &lt;strong&gt;judge&lt;/strong&gt; people, you have no time to &lt;strong&gt;love&lt;/strong&gt; them.”&lt;/em&gt; This is the problem with contemporary society. Instead of judging others, if only we could accept and accommodate the diversity in society, the world would be much less stressful and enjoyable to live and let live. The malaise of intolerance can be neutralized only if we recognize and acknowledge that it exists. Denial doesn’t solve any of our problems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;strong&gt;time-tested triple vaccine that does wonders in preparing the society to free itself from the legacy of intolerance.&lt;/strong&gt; I would call it the &lt;em&gt;Triple E Vaccine – education, empowerment and engagement&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Public education&lt;/em&gt; should inculcate positive values such as social inclusion, scientific temperament, empathy and self-care. &lt;em&gt;Empowerment&lt;/em&gt; of women is the single most important mantra for eliminating intolerance in society. Focus of education should also prepare individuals to think and act freely without surrendering oneself to manipulative brain washing. &lt;em&gt;Engagement&lt;/em&gt; in governance should go much beyond the electoral participation if intolerance is to be erased from various walks of life. Transparency of policies and processes prepares the ground for an engaged society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The danger of not being clear what and how much should be tolerated in the name of liberalism was brought out by Karl Popper, an influential Austrian social scientist of the 1940’s. He coined a powerful expression for the dilemma of liberalism - &lt;em&gt;“The Paradox of Tolerance.”&lt;/em&gt; He wrote in his 1945 book, &lt;em&gt;The Open Society and Its Enemies&lt;/em&gt;, “If we extend unlimited tolerance even to those who are intolerant, if we are not prepared to defend a tolerant society against the onslaught of the intolerant, then the tolerant will be destroyed, and tolerance with them.” Wily politicians often promote intolerant fringe outfits as a bait to provoke the sensibilities of the larger tolerant majority. They have grown their influence by fishing in troubled waters and they are hesitant to let go of the time-tested technique.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The solution lies in increased citizen awareness of the &lt;strong&gt;value of inclusion, diversity, tolerance and mutual support.&lt;/strong&gt; It is the duty of every right-thinking person to promote free thinking, respect of divergent views and empowerment of the marginalized. Parenting and schooling have to have more focus on social orientation and building positivism. Instead of branding academic activism as a threat, it should be seen more as opportunity for fast tracking the social evolution. Universities should be seen as and encouraged to be melting pots of diversity where free thinking and shared vision can be curated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the ripe age nearly seventy five, Indian democracy needs to be confident enough to encourage dialogue, dissent, debate and alternative thinking. Suppressed dissent is more a sign of weakness than strength.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ravi Kumar Pillai is an author, consultant, coach and mentor based in Trivandrum&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/dissent/diversity/intolerance/2020/06/26/anatomy-of-intolerance.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/dissent/diversity/intolerance/2020/06/26/anatomy-of-intolerance.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>dissent</category>
        
        <category>diversity</category>
        
        <category>intolerance</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Looking Beyond the US Elections 2020 – an Indian Perspective</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump seems to have hit a sticky patch even as the US Presidential election is inching closer. He has spent much of his first term indulging in whimsical and mercurial rants. During his term, the US lost much of its strategic clout, racial fire has been stoked through reckless pandering to the white middle-class voters. Even the traditional allies of America are wondering about the next moves of the highly unpredictable POTUS.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his last few days of the term, he seems to be bent upon dousing the most important spirit that has been the life and soul of the legendary American Dream. He wants to block the flow of talent from outside the US and &lt;em&gt;protect the local jobs&lt;/em&gt;. This single retrograde step is contrary to all that the US has stood for. Look at the US President talking like a third world politico!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trump has been boasting about the economy doing well in his rule. The question that many observers ask is whether the US economy has done well in the recovery path from the prolonged lag-effects of the 2008 crisis in spite of Trump’s tantrums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The way he has handled the pandemic put enormous cost on the economy and exposed the inadequacies of the US Healthcare in providing timely, efficient and inclusive support to American people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The burst of pent up black anger across America in the context of the police brutality resulting in two gruesome deaths at the hands of police vitiated the already tense and disturbed sensibilities of the average American. The spontaneity of the outrage of US citizenry- white, black, brown and of all hues- to the killing of George Floyd, an unarmed Black man by suffocation at the hands of a white policeman who held him down shows that the American spirit of liberalism and inclusiveness still runs deep. Trump would probably have been taken aback by the intensity of the rebellion against the act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Covid mess-up and &lt;em&gt;Black Lives Matter&lt;/em&gt; protests have put sudden breaks on a seemingly ‘within reach’ shot by Trump at an extended Presidency for another term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pre-poll surveys now show a clear lag of over ten percent for Trump against Joe Biden, the presumptive Democratic candidate. Not that Joe had distinguished himself as the Vice President in the Obama regime. He was one of the lack-lustre ‘Veep’s in US history. Obama’s compassion and genuine concern for the ordinary American carried the day for Joe too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like negative votes might trump Donald in the hustling. Very similar to the trend in most democracies, where vote for change rides very often on the shoulder of frustration and disappointment with an incumbent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still months to go for the elections. Anything can happen to put Trump back on track for another win. But as of this moment, he seems to be in for a losing battle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donald Trump’s signature posturing has been to offer to mediate ( shall we read ‘meddle’) in any dispute or apparent dispute between sovereign nations. It is to the credit of India and China that we have not given any seriousness to his almost instantaneous offer for help in the Eastern Ladakh incident. If the reported agreement to pull back does hold, both India and China should introspect as to the need for mutual respect, dignity and accommodation. As the geography with nearly 40% of world population and as the two promising economies to lead global recovery post pandemic, both nations and the world have much to lose by mindless adversity. Anyway, the Region has to look beyond Trump and to a shared mutuality of interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For India, a brewing challenge – in fact one of the many simmering challenges – would be to reset the relationship with a possible Democratic Administration post the 2020 US elections. Earlier, Indian origin citizens in the US were by default mostly democratic supporters. But over the past few elections, as the Indian diaspora has become more confident, competent and engaged in the domestic politics of America, they have been able to tactically position on either side of the political spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;US Bureaucrats and Military Brass have traditionally demonstrated visible disdain to India and bias towards Pakistan in their South-Asia diplomacy. Stalwarts like Henry Kissinger, Madeline Albright and Colin Powell irrespective of Democrat-Republican orientation saw India as a satellite of the USSR; they saw India’s assertion of being “non-aligned” as a mask to hide the reality of being aligned against US interests. With the collapse of USSR, we had a chance to reset the equation. But it was Communist China that stole the opportunity from us and they succeeded in leveraging the situation to claw into a powerful positioning both economically and politically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s experience with Trump was not particularly great, as indeed was the experience of many nations caught in the web of his unpredictable twists and turns, lack of awareness or interest in the nuances of global sensitivities. In the current global context, India has to walk a tight rope and manoeuvre with grace, tact and firmness in our relations with the super power of the world and the second-in-line. Our success in crafting ‘Chanakyan’ smart diplomacy coupled with bold economic moves could trip the runner-up to the third position. But for that we indeed need an India 2.0.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether Trump stays or Biden takes over, India cannot let the guard down. If the enemy is powerful, it doesn’t hold us back from learning a few of his tricks and improvising them. We can definitely learn a few smart diplomacy and fine balancing from China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In dealing with US Administration post the upcoming elections, India has to do the homework right, pitch the strategy with firmness and play to win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;*The author is consultant, coach and mentor and can be contacted at ravikumarpillai9@gmail.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 23 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/diplomacy/india/trump/2020/06/23/looking-beyond-the-us-elections-2020-an-indian-perspective.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/diplomacy/india/trump/2020/06/23/looking-beyond-the-us-elections-2020-an-indian-perspective.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>diplomacy</category>
        
        <category>india</category>
        
        <category>trump</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Challenges of Dealing with China</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;If there is one thing common between Nehru and Modi it is that both made sincere attempts to cultivate what they believed to be a natural and sustainable friendship between India and China. Both were back-stabbed by the dragon with its wry and deceptive smile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;China has come a long way from being an outcast on the margins of legitimacy to be a global power awaiting the crowning as &lt;em&gt;‘numero uno’&lt;/em&gt; in global economy.&lt;/strong&gt; In spite of a history of suppressed human rights at home and outright muscle flexing on global arena, how did China succeed in its obsessive pursuit of power so far? It would remain an enigma of human history how Chinese Communist Party turned an intrinsically humanistic economic philosophy of Karl Marx into a medium to shore up its version of crass nationalism and couched capitalism. Even Marx might turn in his grave at the Chinese marauding of his concept of universal working-class unity transcending nationhood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bullies are created when they are empowered by circumstances and myopic public opinion to brazenly challenge norms, conventions and decorum. It is ironic that the world’s largest democracy and the world’s most powerful democracy played key roles in bestowing legitimacy and empowerment to a beleaguered Peoples’ Republic of China (PRC). When the United Nations was set up, China (Republic of China-ROC) was made one of the five permanent members, because among other reasons the USA saw the move as a counter weight to its arch-rival of the time, Russia. However, after the Revolution led by Mao Zedong and the establishment of PRC in mainland China, ROC operated from Taiwan and continued as a Permanent member of the UN, though without any clout comparable to the other four permanent members. India was offered by the US to take up the seat replacing ROC as one of the five Permanent Members. But Nehru saw it as an unethical move and was against upsetting the sensitives of the beleaguered PRC. He declined to take up the offer. China repaid the unwavering support of Nehru by launching a crushing military attack and capturing a large chunk of India in 1962. The immediate provocation was again the humanitarian gesture by Nehru of granting asylum to the persecuted Holy Dalia Lama of Tibet. The Indian territory still in China’s possession as of now is larger than the state of Kerala. &lt;strong&gt;In one of the many ironies of history, non-aligned India and pacifist Nehru became instrumental for the early vetting of the Chinese thirst for blood. The bully of later years was baptized.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India was the first nation in the world to recognize PRC. If Nehru played a part in imparting political legitimacy to PRC, it was left to Richard Nixon, the US President known more for Watergate scandal, to handhold China into diplomatic prominence. Nixon became the first US President in history to visit China in 1971. On Oct. 25, 1971, the United Nations General Assembly voted to admit the People’s Republic of China and to expel the Republic of China. Eight years later, President Jimmy Carter formally recognized People’s Republic of China (PRC) with effect from 1, January, 1979.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was the persistent lobbying by American business - which senses a huge market in the vast Communist republic - that pushed the cascading events in favour of China. US diplomats saw the opportunity to corner the Cold War foe USSR by fostering China as a counterweight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What India, a liberal democracy of huge size could not achieve, was a relative cakewalk for the totalitarian state.&lt;/strong&gt; China managed not only to wriggle out of isolation but to position itself as a beneficial business destination for US companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While China mastered power politics and economic enticement to win over the mecca of capitalism, India cemented its image as a soft, and in the eyes of many global observers, a weak, lethargic third world nation in the mould of many newly independent African and Asian countries. If we wove an entropy of status quo and mediocrity around our global image, those who wielded power for decades should answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the intriguing tale of the ascendancy of China, &lt;strong&gt;the innumerable occasions they used veto power as permanent member to scuttle India’s strategic interests in the UN accentuate our helpless image.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How do we deal with the current China with its unabashedly aggressive posturing and ambitious economic adventurism? In the context of the current geopolitics, most of the Asian and African economies have become firmly entrenched in the Chinese debt trap. The Belt and Road Initiatives, ostensibly to revive the legendary silk rout to rejuvenate global trade, is in reality proving to be a noose around the neck of many nations enticed by the Chinese whisper. Some like Pakistan and Sri Lanka are in the course of diving into depths of debt while their economies come increasingly in the grip of Chinese companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In today’s global supply chain, businesses in US, Europe or in India have a heavy dependence on China&lt;/strong&gt; for sourcing parts, components and intermediaries. Chinese investment globally, including in India, is quite high and well dispersed among sectors. Indian companies have also leveraged their positions in Chinese market. Global trade is intricately meshed into a cross-border value chain and fund flow. It is no longer feasible or advisable to regress into an inward-looking isolation in today’s connected world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this situation, dealing with China has to be done with resolute calmness, strategic maturity and outright pragmatism.&lt;/strong&gt; Gone are the days when emotions could dictate a tit-for-tat adversity. Our national aspirations are global and our current opportunities are immense to grab a much more influential share of global value chain. &lt;em&gt;Creating an atmosphere of unease and uncertainty about India is exactly the game plan of China&lt;/em&gt; as it is rattled by the possibility of losing out the label of the unquestioned manufacturing base for the world. It is in our long-term interest to project India as reliable, secure and strong partner for manufacturing, trade and services. Composure, resilience and long-term focus are signs of potential winners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Hawkish talk of immediate retaliation is not a winner’s strategy. The competent and confident player bides time and strikes with force.&lt;/strong&gt; China needs to be played with the same cunning variations in strategy and strike as it displays. China maneuvered into a position of strength early in the mind game with India by branding Pakistan as ‘all-weather friend.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to cultivate a larger, reliable and globally spread circle of friends and strategic partners and also help Indian private corporate sector to enhance their global reach and influence. We need to craft sustainable alliances and partnerships with strong economies not necessarily limited to US.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Acupuncture is a Chinese treatment that involves inserting very thin needles through a person’s skin at specific points on the body, to various depths.&lt;/em&gt; It goes by the logic that pain cures pain. For China’s illogical and narcissist global transgressions, it needs to be paid back in its own medicine. But the challenge is to do it with finesse, taking global sensitivities and our own geo-political and commercial interests into account.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried to list down my perspective of a &lt;strong&gt;five-point strategy for dealing with China&lt;/strong&gt;. The original &lt;em&gt;panchsheel&lt;/em&gt; proposed by Nehru failed because it was built on emotional premises ignoring possible realpolitik undercurrents. We need to reset the strategic framework to take on a belligerent dragon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;strengthen our military capabilities and infrastructure&lt;/strong&gt; in visible and substantial terms. &lt;strong&gt;Upgrade border surveillance&lt;/strong&gt; deploying state-of-the art technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secondly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;cut off the long rope given by us to fledgling nations trying to curry favors with China&lt;/strong&gt;; forget about ‘long standing relations’, if they only hurt us. We all know who plays the strings when we see contrived chicanery from unexpected quarters that thrived for years on Indian hospitality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;boost Indian economic and commercial interests in the vast hinterland&lt;/strong&gt; where the Chinese have been grazing with greed for years. Leverage the Indian corporate strengths in sectors like construction and manufacturing and bolster the funding pipeline. Forge transnational consortia with countries and institutions for third country investments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourthly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;show pragmatism and flexibility to separate economic and political sides of our China relations.&lt;/strong&gt; We must increase and not reduce mutual economic engagement with China and take it to a point where we make the balance of payment in our favour. &lt;em&gt;Make the corporate and trade ties so strong that China would find it difficult to bully us into submission&lt;/em&gt; because their businesses would get hurt more than ours. For years US and China followed a love-hate relationship while mutual economic interactions thrived. When business and income are involved, negotiations do get sober. Rocking the boat is not a matured option for either side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifthly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;hurt China most where they are most vulnerable&lt;/strong&gt;. They are overly sensitive to the chorus of &lt;strong&gt;human rights abuses and oppressive political management of dissent in China&lt;/strong&gt;. We should play mind- games with the same dexterity and sharpness as they do. We should use our strengths as an open, liberal democracy to highlight, influence and encourage the ‘people issues’ in China that get swept under the carpet in the totalitarian culture there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India and China together have a population of 2.8 Billion – we are home to 38% of the world population. We are neighbors with long shared boundary. &lt;em&gt;There is simply no way we can and should live in perpetual animosity at the people-to-people level.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In 1957, China forcibly occupied and built roads in Aksai Chin area; India came to know of it after one full year. We have come a long way from that position.&lt;/strong&gt; Today, we are able to set the agenda, push our infrastructure in the border areas aggressively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet, we have miles to go. But our path should be far from blind confrontation or meek submission. When a strong nation talks, the world listens. Let us aspire to be heard; let us talk sense with calm and firmness.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/global%20bully/china/ladakh%20blues%20/2020/06/20/challenges-of-dealing-with-china.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/global%20bully/china/ladakh%20blues%20/2020/06/20/challenges-of-dealing-with-china.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>global bully</category>
        
        <category>china</category>
        
        <category>ladakh blues </category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Practice of Self-Compassion</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Sushant Singh Rajput was an extremely talented and ambitious actor. His performances had a refreshing glow and authenticity that was rare to come by so early in career. He impressed as a rank outsider who by his tenacity and commitment was on the verge of breaking out big time on Bollywood. The news-break about Sushant putting an end to his life was shocking and unbelievable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did a successful, young actor with a promising career ahead of him opt to commit suicide? This is not by any means an isolated incident. Why do children, brought up in pampered care decide to end their lives apparently on as frivolous a reason as not getting a smart phone of choice or not being allowed to have free access to internet? What drives young lives with great potential to descend to despair, isolation and despondency? Apparently, something seems to have gone awfully wrong in the emotional well-being of our society.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social connect and active interactions are critical to emotional health. Isolation and insecurity make an unsettling potion for distress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The horrifying loneliness that cracks the will to survive is why solitary confinement is deemed to be one of the deadliest forms of punishment. I remember waiting with bated breath for the live BBC telecast of Nelson Mandela walking out of prison in 1990 after internment for 27 years. He wrote in his autobiography, ‘The Long Walk to Freedom’&lt;em&gt;,&lt;/em&gt; “In those years, isolation became a habit. We were routinely charged for the smallest infractions and sentenced to isolation. &lt;em&gt;I found solitary confinement the most forbidding aspect of prison life. There was no end and no beginning; there is only one’s own mind, which can begin to play tricks”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His eyes radiated an intense mix of forgiveness and calm as he took his first few steps as a free man after spending much of his active years confined to the jail. There was no remorse, no anger visible. But then, everyone is not Nelson. Most human beings tend to wilt under the burden of social disconnect. Despondency tends to take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For snapping social engagement, one need not be in confinement. While living amidst our folks, we can still emotionally experience lack of care, support and comfort. Disengagement within family, community and the larger society takes a toll on the emotional resilience of individuals. Since no two human beings are alike, their response to failures, disappointments and uncertainties would vary too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Emotionally most people are like an iceberg; what is visible and experienced by others is just a tiny bit of us. &lt;strong&gt;People form opinions and judgement of one another based on incomplete and subjective perceptions.&lt;/strong&gt; Our self-image, emotional regulation, relationship building and messaging define our social behavior. In the fast paced and increasingly competitive world, most people are in a rat race to grab opportunities, outsmart competitors and score brownie points.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Expectations and comparisons are the sources of most of our emotional vulnerabilities.&lt;/strong&gt; As children grow up, their parenting, instructional and social experiences tend to reinforce negativity as much as positive feelings. Life experiences are not a zero-sum game; those with predominantly unsatisfying and nourishing emotional experiences as children go on to face adult life with their baggage of skewed beliefs and perceptions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on studies by LANCET, the prestigious international medical journal and the estimates by World Health Organization, &lt;strong&gt;as of 2019 the number of people in India with manifested mental disorders or proneness to them is in the range of 200 to 250 million.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Out of this nearly 100 million suffer from two of the most common emotional distresses – depression and anxiety syndromes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Depression has been cited as the primary motivator in more than fifty percent of all suicides, globally.&lt;/strong&gt; Persisting depression can trigger great emotional pain and loss of hope, inhibiting ability to face adversities with resilience. Pent up frustrations and repeated failures may drive people with fragile self-image to drug abuse, alcoholism or the extreme step of ending own life. &lt;strong&gt;These actions are punishment inflicted on self just like an irate parent trying harsh methods to discipline a child&lt;/strong&gt;. Here, individuals perceive own self as an adversary not worthy of love, kindness and compassion. &lt;em&gt;As a society, we in India do not teach children to recognize, comfort and encourage themselves, though we would like to cultivate the very same behaviors in children towards others.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is here that the relevance of positive psychology comes in. &lt;strong&gt;Positive psychology&lt;/strong&gt; is the &lt;em&gt;science of wellness, positivism, goodness and accommodation&lt;/em&gt;. Happiness and well-being are essentially behavioral in nature. Positive psychology has heavy imprints of the oriental philosophy. Buddhist ideal of compassion is at its core. The concepts of &lt;em&gt;Karma, Maya and Yoga&lt;/em&gt; have a great influence on positive psychology. A belief in the cause and effect theory is underscored by most religions. “A man reaps what he sows” says The Bible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Behaviorally, emotional imprints of our actions get stored in memory. Later experiences get interpreted in the context of our past actions. Remorse and frustration about life events and experiences could lead to self-guilt and lowering of self-image. Conscious practice of goodness, compassion and accommodation would enhance the feeling of wellness in us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;American Psychologist Martin Seligman, who did commendable work on the science of wellness, proposed the &lt;strong&gt;PERMA framework of positive psychology – P for Positive emotions, E for Engagement, R for Relationships, M for Meaning or Purpose and A for Accomplishment or Achievement.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;These five elements would contribute immensely towards building and nurturing a culture of inclusion, empathy and happiness.&lt;/em&gt; It is possible to develop these finer shades of emotional well-being through guided practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within positive psychology, Self-Compassion is a powerful concept. Dr. Kristin Neff was motivated by Buddhist meditation to pursue her doctoral research in self-compassion. She took up self-compassion research and training with a missionary zeal. &lt;strong&gt;Having self-compassion means being able to relate to yourself in a way that’s forgiving, accepting, and loving, even in stressful context.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-Compassion has three pillars:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ø &lt;strong&gt;Kindness&lt;/strong&gt; : Being kind and understanding toward oneself when experiencing pain or failure rather than being harshly self-critical. &lt;em&gt;Love your own self and care to give the emotional soothing to your inner self at times of stress&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ø **See the Big Picture: **Perceiving one’s experiences as part of the larger human experience rather than seeing them in isolation. &lt;em&gt;Ability to perceive any unpleasant event as part of the continuum of life experiences&lt;/em&gt; would motivate us to seek opportunities for self-improvement rather than worry about obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ø &lt;strong&gt;Mindfulness :&lt;/strong&gt; Living in the present moment and making things happen rather than worrying about the past or over-expectations about future. If today, this moment is what matters most, we put our best efforts on the action on hand. &lt;em&gt;“Karmanyeva Adhikaraste”&lt;/em&gt;, says Bhagavad Gita. Focus on Action and the consequences would follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you are down, when things don’t seem to be going your way, that is when you need support, a shoulder to lean on. What if the support, when you need it most, is offered by the one who knows you inside out – your own self? If you are capable of getting into an objective dialogue with self, argue it out with your own consciousness about the need to change course, you would generate immense positivism, openness and critical thinking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Self-Compassion would logically lead to increased self-awareness, self-regulation and resilience. When you are your own best friend and at the same time the most constructive critic of yourself, the process of self-dialogue would turn out to be an enriching experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All of us would feel tense at times, depressed and desperately in need of soothing emotional strokes. With practice and commitment, we can convert our inner self to be the best friend ever. The key to that is mindfulness. Living in the present. When we live in the present, there is little time for remorse or self-pity. We don’t live among fancy dreams of tomorrow nor do we lament over lost chances. &lt;em&gt;Reflect, journalise and critically review your own experiences. Spend a brief fifteen-minute session at the end of each day counselling and mentoring yourself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This way, we can neutralize our small irritations and tiny disappointments from building up to be formidable avalanche that could derail emotional stability, composure and sound reasoning. We owe it to ourselves to take good care of self. Once we are at peace with ourselves, our empathy, relation and communication with others would also be on healthier footing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time positive psychology becomes an integral part of our school curriculum. Seeds of a healthier and happier society need to be sown early in life.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/self-compassion/behavior/psychology/2020/06/18/practice-of-self-compassion.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/self-compassion/behavior/psychology/2020/06/18/practice-of-self-compassion.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>self-compassion</category>
        
        <category>behavior</category>
        
        <category>psychology</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Indian Telecom : Do not Kill the Golden Goose</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;As the Supreme Court of India took up the contentious issue of Adjusted Gross Revenue (AGR) and computation of arrears payable by the Telecom Operators on last Thursday, the flip-flop of our bureaucratic governance was exposed for the umpteenth time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bench headed by Justice Arun Mishra raised questions on the demand raised on the PSUs and said that its verdict in the case was misinterpreted. Issuing demand notes for arrears of license fees to non-Telecom PSUs in Oil and Gas and Power sectors  was unwarranted according to the Court. The contentions before the Court related to the Private operators who had been asked related to pay huge dues on account of pending licence fee and interest for delays. The Court also asked the Private players to submit a detailed schedule  for the deferred dues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Telecom scenario in India as it has panned out since liberalization needs a serious and critical look at this juncture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this time, when the nation is reeling from the fall out of the pandemic lock-down and mass reverse migration, telecom has provided the life-line for regaining a semblance of normalcy. &lt;strong&gt;The Telecom infrastructure has proved to be a silver lining in the current scenario of economic and emotional distress.&lt;/strong&gt; With gaps in their resources , the Telecom sector has struggled hard in the wake of the pandemic to maintain and even enhance service quality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine what would have been the scene if a situation like this had arisen a couple of decades back. The strain would have been several notches more severe than what we are just going through. The Telcos contributed immensely to avoid the lock-down from becoming a full-blown choke-down of the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Both connectivity and capacity were issues that the industry was already struggling with&lt;/em&gt;. But the surge in data traffic in the lock-down exceeded all expectations. The unprecedented uptick was a combined effect of &lt;strong&gt;massive shift from office to Work-From-Home (WFM) protocol as well as higher frequency of virtual meetings, video-streaming and gaming activities.&lt;/strong&gt;  Academic and governance uses also added to the pressure on the networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the past three months alone,  data and video traffic increased by approximately 50% year-on-year.&lt;/em&gt; It is to the credit of the beleaguered Telcos that they rose to the challenge and by and large provided quality and efficient service.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an infrastructure sector baptized in fire, Indian Telecom was struggling to drag itself through bureaucratic rigmarole, funding and execution woes over the past couple of decades. &lt;strong&gt;Every stage from issue of licenses and release of spectrum to going through consolidation was plagued by opacity and tentativeness on policy and procedures.&lt;/strong&gt; “Left to fend for itself” could aptly summarize the plight of the sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Weak-kneed operators folded up and some opted for merger with the more resilient players. In fact, weeding out unviable players is a healthy growth path for telecom in nascent markets. &lt;strong&gt;However, the pain and rigors of regulatory and legal vacillations made a tall demand on the endurance capacity of the surviving players.&lt;/strong&gt; The newest kid on the block, Reliance Jio, charted out a growth path through sheer hard work and deep pockets. In the process Jio not only shook the sector into urgency and proactivity but also built for India a robust fibre network that would probably have taken decades for the Government sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;India’s economic management history is marked by a strange death wish&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;that raises its head from time to time and puts a spoke in the organic growth of business.&lt;/strong&gt; The dilemma of our low global competitiveness stems from structural flaws - a &lt;em&gt;bureaucracy&lt;/em&gt; which by tradition and training &lt;em&gt;acts more like cynical controllers rather than collaborators in execution of development&lt;/em&gt;, rigid and constraining set of &lt;em&gt;laws, often not aligned to the economic realities&lt;/em&gt;, a &lt;em&gt;judiciary mired in delays&lt;/em&gt; and above all a string of &lt;em&gt;myopic political leadership.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Telecom is the lifeline of a digital economy. It is as much essential for survival, sustenance and growth of society as are the basic necessities like shelter, air, water, power and transportation. The 5-G revolution is knocking at our door. If we miss the bus, the digital divide would exasperate and we would lose out the chance to catch up with the developed world on key economic and human development indicators. Scaling up of the connectivity, capacity and security of telecom networks is critical for upgrading our infrastructure including education, healthcare, governance, industry and logistics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the consolidation of the sector, we are left with three major Telecom players - Reliance Jio, Bharti Airtel and Vodafone-Idea. As for the Public Sector player, BSNL, it is unlikely to emerge as a serious and strategic player. It is more likely to remain a laggard; in the best-case scenario it might perhaps evolve into a core network  infrastructure provider offering connectivity, storage and support facilities for the industry. That is ideally the role public sector should play - to act as catalysts in growth. With massive assets in terms of land, Right-of-Way and physical structures, BSNL can leverage and monetize them to gain steady cash flow and support Government.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Going forward, we would see explosive demand for  data, video, storage and security infrastructure.&lt;/strong&gt;  There would be need to invest heavily to build state-of-the-art infrastructure and massively train and upskill talent. We need to build synergistic partnerships of domestic and global manufacturers, service providers, investors and professionals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are we preparing the ground to attract the best in the world to come to India and invest with confidence?&lt;/strong&gt; Are we assuring policy consistency, responsive governmental support and availability of competent local partners, professionals and workforce?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Liberalising  the telecom sector in India started with licensing of a limited number of private operators in metro cities in 1992. The first pan-India licensing was carried out three years later, when 22 circles across India were opened up for private investment. The license fee was required to be paid in annual payments progressively increasing over the period of seven years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The nascent operators had to set up the infrastructure from scratch and had to go through enormous teething troubles and financing issues. In 1999, realizing the gravity of the burden on the operators, Government allowed the operators to switch to a revenue-sharing model instead of the huge fixed license fee. As per the new policy, 15 per cent of Adjusted Gross Revenue (AGR) was to be paid as licence fee. This was later progressively reduced based on pleas by operators to 8 percent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The method of calculating the AGR was disputed by the licensees; they approached the Court seeking to limit the calculation to the income from telecom service provision only.&lt;/strong&gt; They contended that the license related only to telecom operations and therefore it was not justified to include non-operational income such as returns from investments, sale of assets and the like in the calculation of AGR. They lost the case. Through a series of appeals and counter pleas, the issue has lingered on for nearly seventeen years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The matter is now before the Supreme Court. The present plea of the operators, supported by the Government after much dilly-dallying, is for relief by way of staggering, over the next 20 year, the payment of pending dues of license fees and accumulated interest. This awkward situation should not have arisen in the first place. &lt;strong&gt;The strain, delay and erosion of business confidence could have been avoided, if only the policies were drafted with realistic appreciation of the business challenges and investment risks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, we are at a critical juncture requiring massive investment and speedy project execution . The much needed physical, economic and social infrastructure upgrade depends on seamless 5G capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The questions that Supreme Court has asked are core to the transparency and rationale of sound governance&lt;/strong&gt;. It is primary responsibility of the Government to frame, administer and attune the laws, guidelines and procedures in a manner that satisfies legal scrutiny. The outcome of the hearing has enormous bearing on the viability, sustainability and prospects of Telecom in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the Court agrees to  stagger the payment, Department of Telecom (DoT) should ensure fast and flawless follow-up. In the event of Court not agreeing to the deferment, Government should have an alternative strategy to provide relief and support to the sector.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 14 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/telecom/economics/2020/06/14/indian-telecom-do-not-kill-the-golden-goose.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/telecom/economics/2020/06/14/indian-telecom-do-not-kill-the-golden-goose.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>telecom</category>
        
        <category>economics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Vision Overload</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;“If only we had a leadership with vision” is a refrain heard in many democracies. In the hardball political playout, it is often pragmatism and populism that win the day over long-term perspectives. Political parties and leaders tend to prefer short-haul and quick-fix solutions rather than transformational journeys.
Once in a while a leader with rare clarity of thought, eloquence of articulation and ability to inspire the masses emerges on the scene. “Here comes the messiah who would deliver us to the prosperous future, our true destiny”, his followers would vouch. Many free-thinking souls may levitate towards the new-found charisma. An aura gets created around the new hope. A leader is coronated in style.
This may sound straight out of some literary classic, but something close to such fictional ecstasy was visible among the youth, at least in the heartland of India, when Narendra Modi arrived on the staid political arena. Six years have passed since the summer of 2014. Though it looks like the raging pandemic would make a fodder of  the ongoing financial year, it is nevertheless appropriate to ask a plain and simple question. &lt;strong&gt;Whatever happened to the dream that our leader painted for us?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategic leadership is critical to transform the status quo. The leader should be able to articulate a vision, lay out a roadmap with timelines, excite the citizens and ensure execution. &lt;em&gt;Vision, Talent and Execution&lt;/em&gt; make successful change management happen in organizations or the society at large.
Let us examine India’s current state of readiness in terms of each of these three critical success factors for transformation to a globally competitive and confident nation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly, Vision&lt;/em&gt; is quite simply articulating where you want to go. The leader has the responsibility to formulate and convey the message of change powerful enough to excite and engage the citizens.  &lt;strong&gt;The effectiveness of leadership is in ensuring that people at large feel ownership of the change program.&lt;/strong&gt; But if policy formulations are done in the backrooms, away from visibility and devoid of wide participation,  even the best of ideas can fall through in the execution. If people see  the agenda as crafted and imposed from above, their engagement and enthusiasm drop to tepid levels.
It is not grandness of vision or catchiness of slogans that ensure success of transformation. It is the passion that people at large feel from within that motivates ordinary humans to achieve the impossible.
A leader in a hurry could be pushing for newer and newer ideas at breakneck speed. The immediate core group quickly converts them to execution agenda. As the Japanese saying goes, “ &lt;em&gt;If you want to cut the woods in a day, grind the axe for several days to make sure it is sharp”.&lt;/em&gt; Half-baked ideas and tentative implementation schedules could lead to  a policy grid-lock. Unbridled power and low engagement of stakeholders could result in a nagging disconnect in the execution pipeline.
The past few years have generated a &lt;strong&gt;vision overload&lt;/strong&gt; in governance. We seem to have hurtled from one initiative to another with little patience to follow through and bring them to sound closure. Skill India, Start-up India, Make in India, Beti Padao Beti Bachao, Atm Nirbhar Bharat. The list is rather long. Just like power overload would trip the grid, excess of programs would result in lack of engagement, blurring of focus and ineffective monitoring.  In management parlance, it is better to focus on a handful of initiatives and execute them well than spread our attention, resources and efforts too thin. &lt;strong&gt;Focus and prioritisation&lt;/strong&gt;  are critical success factors for any program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reform is key to realising the vision.&lt;/strong&gt;  Reforms should cover the four areas that the PM highlighted in his policy pronouncements - land, laws, labour and liquidity. Again, &lt;strong&gt;the prescription is fine, but who would deliver, how fast and how firmly.&lt;/strong&gt; All these, especially Land and Labour, are sensitive and have political overtones. The Government would be called upon to demonstrate political will, courage of conviction and the ability to absorb shocks if structural reforms are to be implemented seamlessly. &lt;em&gt;In the Indian political structure, major reforms are possible only by building consensus and working hand-in-hand with the States.&lt;/em&gt;
Vision therefore needs to be tempered, refined, focused and supported by the structure and processes to ensure inclusive and participative implementation. A task that requires outreach, accommodation and empathy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Talent is the second strategic pillar of transformational governance. Competence at both political and bureaucracy leadership layers need to be enhanced and aligned to the vision.  Howsoever imaginative and clearheaded the individual at the helm may be, governance effectiveness would greatly depend on the expertise, agility and proactivity of the administration tasked with translating the vision into action.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Independent observers have commented about the lack of administrative experience in the current political leadership team at the centre.&lt;/strong&gt; Except a handful of individuals with originality, guts and creative thinking, there is a discernible gap in talent at the top. A number of leaders with vast experience, courage of conviction and creative thinking have been left out while forming the cabinet. &lt;em&gt;With the aggregate talent of political administration spread rather thin,  we have been having a largely presidential style of governance at the federal level.&lt;/em&gt;  Collectivism, collaboration and respect for opposition have been given short shrift.
The situation is broadly akin to contemporary US where the vertical political divide is so pronounced that consensus building is almost impossible. &lt;strong&gt;From one-upmanship to accommodation is a retrieval in style that both ruling and opposition sides need to traverse.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A strong layer of planning and detailing is required in between visioning and execution to ensure smooth and effective transmission of ideas into action. In governance this crucial layer comprises of the Ministers, Secretaries and their immediate teams. The flip-flops in policy formulation and flaws in documentation as reflected by many instances of amendments and corrigendum on key notifications are  symptomatic of a misalignment between political leadership and bureaucracy. &lt;strong&gt;We need to beef up the  mid-level bureaucracy by inducting talent from academics and industry.&lt;/strong&gt;  Government needs to pursue the recent initiative of scouting for external talent for strengthening the depth of bureaucracy.
&lt;em&gt;Thirdly,&lt;/em&gt; and most importantly,  &lt;strong&gt;execution seems to be the Achilles Heel of the Government.&lt;/strong&gt; The key difference between Modi, the successful Chief Minister and Modi, the all-powerful Prime Minister apparently is the uncharacteristic slackness in implementation that has befallen his stint at national leadership. &lt;strong&gt;Vision overdrive coupled with execution fatigue is the twin aliment that seems to pullback the dispensation from realising its full potential.&lt;/strong&gt;
Leadership is not a solo race, definitely not a 100 meters dash. It is more of a relay race. Collaboration ensures that stakeholders are aligned with the vision and strategies. In a democracy, there is need for healthy interfaces and pursuit of synergies between Centre and States, Ruling and Opposition parties, Government and Industry as well as Business and Academics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A course correction is not something that a truly transformational leader fights shy of.&lt;/strong&gt; If you are pursuing to transform a nation of 1.3 billion people in the current situation of unprecedented crisis, change should start at the top. And the most difficult of the changes is the willingness and openness to admit the need for change to start with own style and messaging. That is the challenge that confronts the very top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The destiny of the ordinary citizens of this country depends on this single choice that the leader will make.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/one/two/2020/06/10/vision-overload.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/one/two/2020/06/10/vision-overload.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Next Wave - From Mixed Economy to a Blended One</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;When Winston Churchill assumed office as the Prime Minister of Great Britain, the country was staring at impending disaster. Serious questions were being raised as to how ‘great’ Britain’s  precarious position would allow it to be and for how long. His resoluteness and perseverance made him a legend for subsequent generations. Most nations today are mired in hopeless economic logjam and deep fissures are visible in their polity. Now more than ever, the world misses  bold and aggressive leaders in the mould like Churchill, Margaret Thatcher or Ronald Reagan. Those  who would cast away their  legacy of political grand-standing and embrace challenges with unwavering commitment to turnaround.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What about India? Are we up to the task of competing effectively with China, let alone hoping to be the next growth engine that the world is desperately searching for? Is our leadership inspiring us to come through the tough times?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Global rating agencies are showing a rare consistency in declaring that all is not well with India’s plans and programs to get back to growth path. The new scenario demands that we match the tough and steep asking rate thanks to after-effects of the pandemic. Amidst the social media orchestration of the ‘infallibility’ of the leader, for once someone needs to be the child who would blurt out , “ But mom, where are the emperor’s clothes?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Much has been written about the patchwork programs announced to address the immediate problems of employment, income and food security at the bottom of the pyramid. But what about the big, bold steps needed to overhaul the economy for the anticipated leap? Confusion and contradictions seem to prevail on the policy front and as in the past we are likely to blame the opportunity once it passes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether from 10 Janpath or Nagpur, remote control has always been the norm for the World’s largest democracy. It is the form not the content, context not urgency of purpose that has mattered in Indian politics over the years. Our leaders seem to be experts in bringing out the same old tricks from the strategy hat like the street magician who has run out of options. What else can explain the clamoring for self-reliance, a euphemism for inward looking complacency that compromises on quality and global competitiveness? It would be naïve to think of restricting  access to our market and at the same time  hoping that the world would roll out the red carpet for our products. Who would come to India to invest and manufacture here if we pride ourselves in our  ostrich-like approach to global trade?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Indian cuisine, khichdi is a very popular, wholesome and all-seasons food made by cooking rice, lentil and a variety of locally available vegetables. The visibility, combination of ingredients and ease to make has made it a synonym for hotch-potch ensembles of policies, products or recommendations. India’s economic structure can aptly be compared to a khichdi.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we gained independence from colonial rule, the pervading antipathy to free trade and private enterprises could be understood. After all, India was colonised by the British who came in as traders; a host of foreign traders and aggressors had subjugated parts of Indian sub-continent even before the arrival of the English sailors. The very foundation of our freedom movement was built upon antipathy to capitalist imperialism. The younger, western educated crop of leaders with Nehru at the helm gave a liberal and socialist tilt to the initial thoughts on  nation building.   The winds of change blowing from the socialist struggles in Russia and parts of Europe also influenced the intelligentsia of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It goes to the credit of the intellectual honesty of the national leadership that in spite of their personal orientations towards mildly left-of-centre policies and their fears about the risks of neo-colonialism, they encouraged serious and open debates about the direction that our economy should take. Both Nehru and Ambedkar advocated state ownership of key industries to drive rapid industrial growth without closing avenues for private enterprise in the country.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notwithstanding his personal views, Ambedkar had the openness and accommodation to declare on the basis of extensive discussions in the Drafting Committee, “What should be the policy of the State, how the Society should be organised in its social and economic side are matters which must be decided by the people themselves according to time and circumstances. It is perfectly possible today, for the majority people to hold that the socialist organisation of society is better than the capitalist organisation of society. But it would be perfectly possible for thinking people to devise some other form of social organisation which might be better than the socialist organisation of today or of tomorrow. I do not see therefore why the Constitution should tie down the people to live in a particular form and not leave it to the people themselves to decide it for themselves”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Compare this erudite stand of Ambedkar with the political expediency of Mrs. Gandhi in even amending the “Preamble” of the Constitution which literally was outside the body of the main text. Or, look at how Narendra Modi Government rushed key amendments through the Parliament with little time for discussion, debate and normalization of opposing viewpoints.  Surely, the lofty values that the framers of our constitution held high were diluted in the alter of practical democracy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mixed economy, which was adopted by us from the outset as we embarked on nation-building,  envisaged co-existence of the Public and Private enterprises with key role to build core infrastructure resting with the Government. The outcome has so far proved to be too tardy and inefficient. In spite of the assigned strategic role, in reality the public sector has yielded the space for dynamism, enterprise and ambition to the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the world talks about India’s corporate diversity and resilience, the discussion predominantly centres around our private enterprises. The robust and aggressive private sector in India can no longer be denied its rightful place in development planning. In mixed economy, we have denied a fair playing field for either the public or the private sector. Instead of getting the best of both worlds, we seem to have accomplished just the opposite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India is too large and complex to make quantum leaps in policies, especially because every five years we have to go before the electorate to seek a fresh mandate. Whatever the inequities and manipulative politics in our society, mathematics of  the voter instincts has in the past swept away predictions of political pundits with impunity. Indira Gandhi or Vajpayee losing the elections despite their projected popularity at the time of going to polls speaks of the triumph of grass-root opinion. It could plainly be that a hapless last-mile citizen in this country votes emotionally and not rationally; but emotions have the potential to alter political equations with vehemence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hence Indian politicians, even those who are committed to change, prefer  incrementalism and tinkering. Attempting substantial  changes has all along been perceived as politically too risky. Transformational leadership, however, is the need of the hour. The paradigm of political expediency needs to be recast. Combining purpose, agility and empathy, we need to dismantle barriers to productivity, efficiency, investment and employment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Three examples would mark the immense potential of private investment to be the game-changer. Take our IT, Automobile and Telecom Sectors. All of them have undergone massive upgrade. The prime mover has been the presence of strategic private players in these sectors. Reliance Jio’s path-breaking initiatives on  digital technologies and platforms are revolutionizing not just communications, but retail and smart applications as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time to articulate a clear policy and thrust for scaling up the volume, technology and business practices. We need to shift from tolerating private investment to encouraging, supporting and incentivizing the best in the world to move in to India. They would  bring in technologies for massive employment opportunities and significantly enhance our share in global trade and manufactured exports. The Government is at last talking on these lines. But as always India is expert in missing the bus of economic growth all too often. Will this time be different?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘Self reliance’ and ‘manufacturing for the world’ are indeed not compatible or complementary polices. Instead of harping on self-reliance and creating tariff barriers, we need to commit ourselves to go up the global value chain by upgrading infrastructure, opening up policy and tariff barriers and launching massive industry-aligned skilling programs in PPP mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope and pray for pragmatism and political will to dawn on our ruling dispensation to take advantage of the window of opportunities thrown up by the current disruptions.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/economy/india/2020/06/05/the-next-wave.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/economy/india/2020/06/05/the-next-wave.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>economy</category>
        
        <category>india</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>In the Wonderland of Indian Public Sector</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Indian politicians usually fight shy of candid and crisp statements. In a rare departure, Nirmala Seetharaman, the Finance Manager recently articulated the modified policy on public enterprises, “In strategic sectors, at least one enterprise will remain in the public sector but private sector will also be allowed. In other sectors, PSEs will be privatized.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Governments across the world do engage in economic activities beyond the strict administrative domains. Even in the advanced OECD Economies, there is a fair sprinkling of State-Owned Enterprises. In India, Government Businesses in the corporate space are referred to as Public Sector Undertakings (PSUs) or Public Enterprises (PEs). I prefer the term ‘enterprise’ rather than ‘undertaking’. The latter connotes operating under compulsions of circumstances, devoid of the passion that goes into a business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had opportunities to work at corporate level both in public and private sectors in India and abroad. My professional tenures, academic interests and consulting experiences enabled me to see public enterprises both from inside-out and outside-in perspectives. I believe what matters for economies and for ordinary citizens is the ability of businesses to give fair return on their social investment. The capital employed in both public and private sector enterprises are slices of the same stock of national wealth. When Air India sinks money or an errand private businessman flees to safe havens, the wealth that gets eroded is predominantly funds from financial institutions, banks or the public. It is time we break free of semantic delusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past few decades, globally the role and scope of governments, state-owned enterprises and private businesses have transformed. Citizens expect Governments to enable human capacity build-up, ensure efficient public services and leverage investment, trade and collaboration across sectors for economic growth. The State is increasingly vacating non-strategic space for competent enterprises in the private sector. The private sector has grown significantly in volume, value and economic impact over the years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pioneering Central Public Enterprises (CPEs) were established in India in the 1950’s and 60’s. They were conceived as cornerstones of the planned economic model. As a newly independent nation, woefully short of private capital, the Government had no choice but to undertake huge investments by itself for building the core infrastructure. Massive greenfield plants sprang up across India in key sectors like Steel, Coal, Heavy Industries, Railways and Defence Production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Soon public enterprises expanded beyond the core sector into many products and services where hardly any justification existed for locking in public finance. The number of CPEs soared also on account of take-over of sick private sector units. The bulge in public enterprises coupled with pedestrian management styles snowballed into a legacy of inefficiency, under-utilisation of capacity, political meddling and creeping mediocrity. A proverbial drag on the economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Public Enterprises scenario became murkier with many State Governments joining the bandwagon and setting up new units. Established as vehicles for employment generation, headed mostly by bureaucrats with little training or interest in managing business, lacking sound business plan or marketing strategy and too small in scale of operations to make any impact commercially, most of these units were destined to fail. Diverting substantial budgetary and borrowed funds to set up Government-owned businesses constrained the much-needed spending in critical social infrastructure like health, education, housing, sanitation, drinking water and electricity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the Standing Committee on Public Enterprises (SCOPE), as of March 2019 there were 350 Central PEs with paid up capital of Rs. 2.75 lakh crores and capital employed exceeding Rs. 26 lakh crores. Their aggregate Return on Capital Employed (ROCE) was a paltry 5.4%, compared to 20% achieved by the BSE- 200 listed companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you add the State Government PEs, the scenario is absolutely grim. The collective annual net loss incurred by State Government PEs alone in FY 2018-19 stood at nearly 80,000 crores. Taken together, the public sector business units in the country have guzzled a sizable chunk of national wealth over the years. Looking at the collective debt of the Central and State PEs viz-a-viz their much eroded Networth, the adverse impact on India’s financial system is humongous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The pandemic disruption and economic uncertainty have brought an urgency to the long pending review and restructure the PEs. Both Central and State Governments should comprehensively review the portfolio of Public Enterprises and classify them into three buckets– Strategic (Must Retain in State control), Tactical (Need to co-exist with private business in the medium term) and Routine (Should let go sooner than later). Each category needs to be tackled with realistic sensitivity to their profiles and prospects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strategic domain would cover very selective and highly critical enterprises involved in futuristic technology, science and national security. These would call for substantial investments, sensitive research and development as well as complex intellectual property protection. Government should logically have the primary role in this group of enterprises. The scope for consolidation and restructuring should nevertheless be examined to eliminate overlaps, avoid infructuous competition and realise possible synergies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the non-strategic areas, closer analysis is needed to identify where tactical intervention would be needed for price-stabilisation, supply chain resilience and market reach to marginal customers. In the tactical segment, strong presence of public enterprises side by side with competing private businesses would boost Governments’ ability to intervene effectively as and when needed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from strategic and tactical enterprises, all other businesses can be privatised through a transparent and competitive process. Where the Networth has eroded beyond repair and the industry is not critical, winding up could also be an option. There is scope for unlocking the economic value of idle or underutilised assets. This locked up wealth when unleashed can add to the kitty to fund physical and social infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While deciding upon the future structure, governance processes, and operating model of the entities that would be retained as public enterprises, we need to consider the following aspects. These are the minimal enabling conditions for sustainability and resilience of any business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, business alignment and economies of scale are critical for the success of public enterprises. Fragmented and overlapping business entities competing for the same customer base is quite common in India. Most PEs especially in the State Government sector are too small and unviable to make any market impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best practices suggest that unless an enterprise is a significant player (say, with at least a third of market share) or is among the top quartile in the industry in terms of revenue and profitability, exit is an appropriate strategy. By monetising the salvageable economic value through asset or stake sale, the enterprise can do belated justice to the key stakeholders, which in the case of PEs means the ordinary citizens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, PEs to be effective need to have both autonomy and accountability. The composition, stability and commitment of the Board of Directors are a concern, especially for the State Government PEs. The Central PEs have a relatively matured process of selection of Board and Executive Management. But the situation in the States is far from comfortable. Tentative tenures of CEO and Board, political interferences and lose control systems result in powerless and disinterested management devoid of direction or commitment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the third aspect of governance of PEs – structural issues. Majority of Public Enterprises, especially in the States, are wholly owned entities of Government with hardly any public stake. Accountability to shareholders, compliance with SEBI and Board level professionalism are the control levers of a listed company. These controls are absent or weak in the PE space, especially in the State Government PEs. Very few State Government companies have listed themselves in the bourses. Gujarat is a notable exception where we have companies in the State sector with decent market capitalisation. Gujarat State Petronet Limited having a market capitalisation exceeding Rs. 5000 Crores and Gujarat Narmada Valley Fertilizers and Chemicals Limited with 1000 Crores are two examples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Private Companies are in reality more ‘public’ than the Public Enterprises. Most of the large private companies are listed in Stock Exchanges and are subject to financial reporting, accountability to shareholders and regulatory control. While a private listed company has to worry about corporate image, shareholder management and compliances, many large PSUs are mired in opacity, save for the CAG Audit and Parliamentary accountability. From an insider perspective I can vouch for the ‘save-the-skin’ attitude of most PE Managements to audit and controls. Audit very rarely leads to constructive follow-up action and strengthening of systems and processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Functional autonomy is severely constrained for the public enterprises. Vigilance, CAG Audit and bureaucratic diktats weave a chakravyuh of restrictive framework in effect creating a culture of action-avoidance among the executive teams. Most key functionaries choose play safe, shun legitimate risk-taking and procrastinate on policy matters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, a crucial element impacting the health and survival of PEs is their funding mechanism. Budgetary support, Government backed loans, commercial borrowings and access to multilateral funding are the common sources of funds for PEs. The fund starved Governments seem to be pouring more resources into the bottomless pits, in many cases just to keep the show of mediocrity on. Easing the capital woes through restructuring, divestment and public listing should be taken a lot more seriously. Periodic review and debt-swapping would also improve financial health of over-leveraged PEs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifthly, the importance of competitive neutrality or maintaining a level playing field between private and publicly-owned businesses is critical for open economies. With matured private businesses present in most sectors, lack of equitable treatment would put players at an undue disadvantage. By giving adequate attention to competitive neutrality, governments can minimise the risk of competition being “crowded out.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is also the burden of social commitments in crisis that falls squarely on the public sector with often inadequate mitigation of the financial impact. PEs should be adequately compensated for undertaking social commitment on behalf of Governments from time to time. Level playing ground implies further that the backdoor access that the private sector traditionally enjoyed should be cut off and transparency in dealings ensured.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sixthly, Human Capital resilience has been flagged as a key concern in the management of public enterprises in various reports. The Boards of State PEs are mostly cluttered with Civil Servants who often wear multiple hats and their tenure is too short or uncertain. Building a professional management cadre for PEs with functional independence remains an illusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, there is a need for realistic and rewarding corporate performance management. The system should involve benchmarking with the best practices in the market, regular monitoring and differentiated executive reward programs. We should be willing to pay the performing executive teams of PEs handsome bonuses comparable to the private sector.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An action plan for transformation of PEs based on the above considerations would propel them to an agile, accountable and socially responsible future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us reset our understanding and sensitivity to privatisation. Whether private or public, classifying businesses into performing and non-performing should be the more meaningful comparison. Afterall in contemporary India, the bulk of employment opportunities, lion’s share of economic value addition and major chunk of GDP contribution are by the vast array of private enterprises built upon the dreams, sweat and toil of individual enterprise. Therein lies the future of our economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time to redraw the mosaic of mixed economy with more realistic appraisal of realities and prospects. Public Enterprises definitely have a strategic space - much more focussed, professional and accountable compared to the past. But the engines of growth for widespread prosperity would be the private enterprises in the country.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/one/two/2018/01/12/wonderland-of-indian-public-sector.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/one/two/2018/01/12/wonderland-of-indian-public-sector.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>What Lies Ahead of the Gulf Slowdown?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Stories from One Thousand and One Nights, popularly known as Arabian Nights, have lighted up the minds of millions of kids in India for generations. Children who grew up listening to these stories by the bedside would have fantasized about the immense riches of Arabia. At least some of them would have migrated to the Gulf later in life in pursuit of job opportunities and savings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Oil-rich Arab monarchies, notably the five Gulf Coordination Council (GCC) nations of Saudi Arabia, United Arab Emirates, Bahrain, Oman and Qatar have played a key role in lifting millions of low-skilled and semi-skilled workers from South Asia to decent living standards. A stint in the Region would have enabled many of them to have a roof over their head and a bank balance to fall back. The newfound prosperity on the back of Gulf remittances is visible not just in Kerala where large houses dot even the rural landscape. In pockets across India with a sprinkling of gulf migrant households, the folklore centres around the local lads who returned with tidy fortunes from across the Arabian sea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Migration to the Gulf countries, just a trickle in the 1960s, picked up momentum as the oil-based economies went into overdrive. Massive construction for oil and infrastructure projects, sweeping retail boom and surging need to service improved lifestyles of the local populace created massive demand for workforce across the GCC countries. Bulk of the migrants from India and neighbouring regions were with little education, practically no job skills and minimal exposure beyond their immediate communities. Many of them would have encountered harrowing experiences at the hands of recruiting agents, money lenders and in some cases even from their local sponsors. Insha Allah, by the Grace of God, the travails did pay off for many. Today, more than 9,000,000 Indian migrants work in the GCC countries and their combined annual remittance is to the tune of nearly USD 50 Billion, according to the IMF.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gulf economies have had a chequered history of geo-political tensions and economic risks. The Region has demonstrated resilience to bounce back from adversities with remarkable agility. The dynamics of oil cartels in adjusting the supply and pricing of crude and the obsession of the US and Western arms exporters for the deep pockets of Gulf States have led to deft moves on the chess board of Arab politics over the years. For the past few years, the Region encountered a series of unsettling news from the Arab Spring protests in Syria in 2010-12 to the raging discord between Qatar and other GCC States. The economic slump of 2008 and fluctuating oil fortunes in recent years have put roadblocks on the dream-run of the region. The Covid-19 pandemic struck at a particularly tough time has hit everyone bringing the global economy on its knees. The lockdown has put enormous strains on the already mellowed economies of GCC countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Migrant labour on whom the Region is heavily dependent has suddenly found itself at the vertex of the worsening scenario. India, a key source nation for labour, is in a particularly uncomfortable position. The Indian expatriate workforce in GCC is worried about the unsettling impact of Covid. In the wake of uncertainty about continuity of employment and earnings, they look up to the Indian Government for repatriation and rehabilitation. There is pressure from the host nations to lighten the migrant stock due to the lingering economic woes of the region. We cannot be insensitive to the genuine concerns of a Region that has had historic ties and shares strategic interests with us. The massive reverse migration that the Government has embarked upon is therefore not only unavoidable but cannot wait any longer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is the future of migrant labour post-repatriation? Is there light at the end of the tunnel? How likely is it that most of the workforce would return to the Gulf sooner than later?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both demand and supply sides of the migrant labour equation are in a state of flux. Market benchmarks on wages are tightening. The labour market and small business confidence are currently on razor’s edge. SMEs who employ bulk of the low and semi-skilled workforce are struggling to keep afloat. Pruning of the expatriate workforce in GCC economies is unavoidable given the construction and business sentiments taking a hard hit in the current economic scenario.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are four key factors that impact the future of labour migration to the Gulf Region. Taken together, their combined effect would be a strategic shift in the volume, velocity, skill-mix, sustainability and earning potential of future migrants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, the National workforce in the GCC countries today has no resemblance to that in the past. Seeking routine and easy-to-train skills from abroad is not a viable strategy any more. The demography of GCC countries is heavily tipped in favour of the younger age groups. The median age of citizens of Gulf countries is in the range of 25-30 years. For the UAE it is around 27 years and for Saudi 30 years. Overall, within GCC a little less than 50% of citizens are in the working age bracket of 15 to 64 years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though Nationals enjoy preference for employment in the Ministries and Government companies, the GCC member states find it difficult to keep adding to the size of the bureaucracy without restraint. The cost to the exchequer is high in view of the attractive salary and benefits package for Nationals, the huge social security obligations and rising expectations for upward mobility among the young entrants to the job market. Efforts to increase private sector employment of Nationals have met with lukewarm response both from employers and the local workforce. In order to provide avenues of employment for the burgeoning National working-age population, most GCC Governments are squeezing out expatriate presence in routine jobs in the retail, trade and commerce segments. With the private sector under severe financial strain, expatriate workers are staring at a gloomy outlook on employment and earnings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Secondly, the macro-economic scenario looks set for a prolonged period of strain. Since oil revenues are the predominant resource for Governments, any slump in global crude prices below the comfort level would be a crisis for the Region. For 2020, the International Monetary Fund (IMF) estimates the breakeven prices for a barrel of oil to cover budgetary requirements of GCC countries as USD 45 for Qatar, USD 54 for Kuwait, USD 91 for Bahrain, USD 83 for Saudi Arabia, and USD 70 for UAE. The current Brent Crude price is below USD 30 per barrel. No wonder, GCC countries are under pressure to prune expenses, boost non-oil revenues and increase tax buoyancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Saudi Arabia has this week announced tripling of VAT on basic goods to 15 per cent and pruning the budgeted spending on major projects by around USD 26 billion. UAE’s economy has had to endure the twin impacts of coronavirus and oil price slump. While Abu Dhabi being an Oil-driven economy was hit hard by the petroleum industry crisis, Dubai which is heavily underwritten by non-oil revenue from trade, transportation, tourism, retail and real estate is feeling enormous heat. The story is similar across the rest of GCC as well. With significantly reduced industrial, commercial and construction activities, it makes economic sense to lighten the migrant labour pie in the workforce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, there is a discernible interest in digitalisation and advanced technologies in the GCC countries. The Region, notably UAE, is in the forefront of the digitalisation push. There is keen interest and commitment to pitchfork the national youth to the next level of digital competence. With wide ranging interest in technology, space, green energies, and bio-medical fields, UAE and other GCC countries in the future are likely to seek expatriate talent in niche areas of expertise. The demand for run-of-the-mill staffing from abroad is set to shrink pretty fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I visualise a scenario where GCC will compete with the Western world for the high-end Asian talent in emerging frontiers of knowledge. The living conditions and benefits offered would also be competitive to advanced economies. “Less in quantity, more in talent” would ideally define the future of Indian workforce in the Gulf. The ongoing reverse migration is to be understood as part of the logical churn in the expatriate workforce in line with the changing economic value profile of the Region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourthly, due to the generational migration among the Indian expatriates in the Gulf, the youth would be increasingly reluctant to seek low-skill employment. We have witnessed closing of the wage gap between the urban job markets in India and GCC locations in the past few years making gulf openings less tempting to skilled and semi-skilled categories from India. With sizeable increase in fresh National job-seekers in coming years, it is quite likely that jobs which were traditionally on offer for Indian and South Asian expatriates would increasingly shift to local youth and the spillover would go in the first instance to low-cost expatriates from the Middle East and North Africa (MENA) Region. The residual manpower demand from India would shift from the traditional hubs of Kerala and Southern states to the Hindi heartland due to cost considerations. The trend is already obvious from the data for 2018, which shows nearly 45% of Indian migrants to the Gulf countries were from the two large North Indian states of UP and Bihar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Economics is defined by cycles of ebbs and tides. I am optimistic that the Gulf States would rebound from the gloom of today to a brighter tomorrow. But cost, strategic skill-localisation and market dynamics would mean that much fewer Indian workers would be present in the emerging Gulf job market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is therefore incumbent upon the federal and state governments in India to handle the issue of returning migrants with imagination, empathy and accommodation. The responsibility to find long term and sustainable solutions to the woes and uncertainties of Gulf returnees can no longer be taken lightly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India has a knack for seeing things from a narrow and short-term perception. But this time, it is an altogether different ballgame. We have no choice but to approach the migrants’ crisis with a holistic and affirmative agenda. It is time to let go of the old habits and fixated ideologies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to open up our economy to massive industrialisation. We have to incentivize investments for scaling up capacities. We have to take reskilling and up-skilling of the workforce a lot more seriously than in the past. Skill India and Make in India initiatives have not taken off the way they should have. Agriculture has to be modernised and upgraded to global standards. We need to incubate a million small entrepreneurs. All these and much more are required to make India ready to provide sustainable employment not just to returning migrants but to the army of domestic jobseekers too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In future, an Indian should ideally become an NRI on the basis of the pull of his skill-set or his burning ambition to compete with the best in the world. If being an NRI is an involuntary choice out of desperation for livelihood, the call for ‘Atm Nirbhar Bharat’ would remain just another slogan. The reverse migration from gulf would hopefully serve as a warning signal to reset and relaunch our skilling and employment strategies.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/economics/2018/01/12/tree-of-codes.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/economics/2018/01/12/tree-of-codes.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>economics</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Practice of Gratitude</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Many years back I was nominated to attend an international training program in a prestigious academic institution in London. Those days in India everything from a passport to foreign exchange had to be arranged within the tight regime controls of the Government. These and many other requirements were rationed out and made to appear as great favour at the mercy of the bureaucrats at different echelons. The self-importance of petty Government officials was perceived as directly proportional to the queues and recommendations for sanctions and signatures. In hindsight, India then resembled the erstwhile East European scarcity-ridden ‘dole-out’ societies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the beginning of the 100-day program, we had an introductory session. The course coordinator, a well-built, graceful Irish gentleman in his forties told us while welcoming, “In this country, let me assure you, two simple expressions can help you to get along and get things done. They are Please and Thank You. My immediate thoughts were, “I wish someone had told me this in my younger days!”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps in the hustle and bustle of getting on with the routines of life, jostling and elbowing our way, breaking queues and a bit of shouting or screaming have all been accepted as ‘normal’ in the Indian way of life. As a society, we seem to take services we get from others as entitlements and hence thanking the service provider is deemed unwarranted. When is the last time you said, “Thank You” to a bank teller, postman or a counter sales person? Or, between spouses, do we exchange thanks once a while?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The public insensitivity to the social need for gratitude is glaring in the ongoing COVID scenario. The healthcare personnel from doctors and nurses to medical attendants and support staff are overstretched and work without proper rest, facilities or good quality protective gear in many cases. Yet, very few in the public express a word of thanks to these critical staff who are putting their personal safety at risk to serve us. Instances of abuses, heckling and even physical attacks on doctors and paramedical staff are reported from many parts of the country. Particularly, the Nurses who are like angels treading on earth are abused, harassed and turned away from residential localities by many ill-informed citizens. Cynicism seems more the norm than exception in social behaviour. Contrast this with nations like Japan and much of SouthEast Asia where politeness, social courtesies and thankfulness are appreciated and encouraged from early stages of life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude is a prime topic of study and research globally even as the discipline of positive psychology has gained prominence. It is now increasingly appreciated that the prime purpose of life is pursuit of happiness; seeking harmony with people and nature opens up the path to sustainable joy. Over the past decade, researchers have identified great social, psychological, and physical health benefits in the simple act of thanksgiving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clarity still eludes scholars on whether gratitude is an emotion or a value. While empirical psychologists see gratitude from an emotional prism, it has an unmistakable spiritual dimension too. Philosophy treats gratitude more as an ethical value. Most religions treat empathy and gratitude as central to their core belief framework. From a psychological or ethical perspective, it is immensely important to feel, express and promote gratitude. Quite simply it makes us better human beings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an open and diverse society, it makes sense to recognize and practice thanksgiving as a secular social behaviour that transcends the prescriptive codes of ethics within narrower religiosity. Gratitude as a social behaviour is of immense value especially in times of crisis. Empirically, gratitude has been linked with positive emotions such as contentment, happiness, pride, and hope. The positivity from gratitude permeates the giver and the taker in substantial measure. It is the mutuality of the behavioural impact of thanksgiving that makes it a really powerful behavioural tool of wellness. A Gallup survey of American teens and adults in 1998 found that an overwhelmingly high share (90%) of respondents felt happier and positive when they expressed thanks for services by others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Harvard Medical School reported a seminal research by two psychologists, Dr. Robert A. Emmons of the University of California and Dr. Michael E. McCullough of the University of Miami on gratitude. They asked all participants to write a few sentences each week focusing on their social experiences. One group wrote about things they were grateful for during the week. A second group wrote about daily irritations or things that had displeased them during the period. After ten weeks, those who wrote about gratitude were more optimistic and felt better about their lives. Their health parameters like sleep quality, blood pressure, sugar level and heart beat during this period were found to be robust. Definitely, feeling grateful for one’s experiences and interactions contributed to positive feelings about self and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As employees, managers or customers, we seek, receive and provide a variety of services on a day-to-day basis. We also opine, recommend and comment upon these services. Those who feel and express gratitude for the services and support received would experience fulfilment and contentment. On the other hand, those who overly rue the unpleasant experiences are bound to be ill-at-ease with self and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude as a habit has to organically evolve as part of emotional maturing through childhood, schooling and socialisation. Like many other aspects of normative social behaviour, gratitude practice has to become second nature by adolescent phase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The psychology of gratitude recognizes three distinct stages of thankfulness - recognizing the contribution of others in our wellbeing, making a mental or documented recording of the events triggering gratitude and expressing the feeling of thankfulness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here are three simple steps in gratitude practice that can initiate individuals to build a thanksgiving culture. These steps are as much relevant and applicable to family or community situations as to the organizational context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude Journal : As the name suggests it is simply a log of the incidents and contributions that you feel grateful for. It is a daily recording of events which you consider significant and have contributed to a sense of fulfilment. The journal can be an unstructured note; but it is desirable to follow a structure by including details like the persons to whom you feel grateful, your expectations from the event and how significantly it impacted you. If you can record the events in story-telling mode describing the behaviours involved and your perceptions and interpretations of the emotional impact on self and other stakeholders, the journal would be more effective as a self-development tool. It is a good practice to review and record the critical events at the end of the day. It enhances objectivity of the self-analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the flip side, gratitude journaling reinforces the habit of gratefulness. On the other hand, many people start a new practice with high enthusiasm but fail to sustain the motivation long enough to have lasting behavioural impact. The practice of gratitude journaling may either not be sustained or can degenerate into a mechanical routine devoid of passion. The individual who embarks upon the practice should be mindful of the need for persistence. It is important to remind yourself through self-talk about the value of the exercise and the need to practice long enough for it to become a habit. That is where the other two steps in the behavioural trilogy would help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude Expression: It is not sufficient to recognize those who serve you and enhance your wellness and fulfilment. You need to express gratitude to the individuals. “Feeling gratitude and not expressing it is like wrapping a present and not giving it, ” wrote William Arthur Ward, the inspirational writer. How true! I am reminded of many parents who love their children immensely but fail to express it leaving scars of neglect and indifference in the psyche of the children even as they grow into adulthood. Similar is the case with thanksgiving. Just imagine how a doctor or a nurse would be overwhelmed by a demonstration of appreciation and warmth by the patients, relatives or general public. Don’t just have gratitude, express it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Expression of thanks can take many forms and the best is a direct, face-to-face ‘thank you’. In the organizational setting, ‘thank you’ notes, surprise treats and on-the-spot celebrations are powerful motivators, much more than monetary incentives. The impact of appreciation is more when the communication happens as close to the trigger event as possible. Hence the power of spot rewards in workplace motivation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gratitude Meditation: Gratitude Meditation is the practice of combining meditation with gratefulness. Many of us do practice meditation. Most religions stress on expressing gratefulness to the Almighty, the Supreme Spirit. Gratitude meditation extends the focus of meditation to the events and people who impact your life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It makes us to sift through our experiences and identify the moments for which we feel gratitude. It has moorings on the Buddhist thought which beseeches us to look for positivity in every moment, even in the rough and tough one. Like the seed deep inside the fruit, every experience has a core of positivity pregnant with possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When individuals and families realise the importance of gratefulness and practice the same, over a period it becomes a social habit. A transformational change in social behaviour can indeed start with individual initiatives. Now is the chance for moving from concept to practice. At the individual level, these three exercises can initiate your journey of gratitude practice. Let us remember when it comes to behavioural learning, you will never get a better teacher than yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the macro level, it makes immense sense for India to think of a designated National Thanksgiving Day. It would formalise a national context for gratitude practice. Of course, there is no need to add another holiday to the plenty that we have. What better choice can there be than to declare the Second of October, Gandhi Jayanthi to be our National Thanksgiving Day? An occasion to celebrate our appreciation for the countless people who made a difference in our lives.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/one/two/2018/01/12/the-practice-of-gratitude.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/one/two/2018/01/12/the-practice-of-gratitude.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>one</category>
        
        <category>two</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
