<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ravi Kumar Pillai</title>
    <description>Author, Coach, Mentor and Consultant</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 17:00:47 +0530</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 08 May 2021 17:00:47 +0530</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.5</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>A Career Survival Guide for Tough Times </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Among the many paradigm shifts in the corporate world over the past few years, the &lt;strong&gt;shortening career shelf-life,&lt;/strong&gt; especially at executive and professional levels, stands out for its emotional impact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my long corporate career in diverse settings, I have had a ringside view of meteoric rises and unceremonious exits in the executive ladder. &lt;strong&gt;Career longevity gets shorter, the higher you move up&lt;/strong&gt;. In my experience, I can count on my fingers the handful the C-Suite occupants who carried their bats through their innings unbruised and could exit with grace and contentment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that many excellent professionals who work their way up lose their sheen and spirit somewhere on the way? What can one do to be better prepared for the inevitably bumpy ride in corporate career?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long gone are the days of &lt;em&gt;‘jobs for life’.&lt;/em&gt; In fact, the very term ‘job’ is a misnomer. In conventional sense, a job is something you do to earn a living by delivering on the tasks entrusted. &lt;strong&gt;The entire concept of job is contractual in nature – you give your effort and get rewarded by salary.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;A quid pro quo.&lt;/em&gt; This idea of job as we understood it in the past is out-of-sync with the expectations, attitudes and aspirations of today’s professionals. &lt;strong&gt;Jobs are out and career is in&lt;/strong&gt;. At least in the corporate sector, that is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the Indian context, many in government and public sector might still see themselves as jobholders and not as being on an exciting career journey. May be, the structural and systemic contours of their jobs do not enthuse them to see their daily chores as potential careers replete with opportunities for growth, satisfaction and rewards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, let us look at the corporate sector and focus on the professional and executive levels to understand the challenges and opportunities of their career management.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corporate career is indeed akin to a plane ride in the Indian monsoon with high chance of being caught in turbulence and air pockets.&lt;/strong&gt; As long as you are flying above the cloud in clear skies, the ride may be smooth. But corporate career is not a smooth ride but involves up moves, dull moments, and to be realistic, downswings as well. Very few successful professionals would be able to look back on their career journey and claim to have had a one-way ascendancy to the top.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If career is not a bed of roses, how would one prepare for minimising the shocks and bumps. There are &lt;em&gt;six survival skills&lt;/em&gt; that can carry you through the rough and tough of professional life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, you need to demonstrate &lt;strong&gt;agility and alignment&lt;/strong&gt; to the changing economic and cultural realities. Most professionals work as part of teams led by a leader. &lt;strong&gt;In reality, most of us are on ‘project mode’ more often than we realise.&lt;/strong&gt; Much like in a combat situation in the army, we have to follow the discipline and SOPs for implementing group tasks. &lt;em&gt;Alignment with the leader is key to effectiveness.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Most workplace stress and discord happen due to the inability of the leader and the team to appreciate each other’s perspectives&lt;/strong&gt;. When there is a leadership change, for example, the new leader is either from within or from outside. The pressures and sensitivities of realignment to the new situation would be tremendous on both the leader and the led.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Very often business continuity is seen from a system or technology point of view. The reality is that much of the continuity conundrum is emotional.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many a time, a team member gets too closely identified with the boss. In the complex workplace politics this could involve a risk of misplaced perception on loyalty and cooperation. Even functional heads might face disruptive shuffling and marginalisation in times of key executive changes. Fear and apprehensions of trust deficit and alignment are seldom dealt with objectively and dispassionately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is therefore important to ensure that one practices diplomacy, tact and objectivity in workplace relationships.&lt;/strong&gt; Also, &lt;strong&gt;the ability to adapt to workplace dynamics with ease and flexibility&lt;/strong&gt; needs to be cultivated as you move up the ladder. Workplace behaviours are shaped additively by our day-to-day interactions and interfaces. &lt;em&gt;Therefore, one needs to consciously cultivate the practice of prudence, regulation and objectivity in relationship management early on in the career.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secondly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;continuous learning and self-renewal&lt;/strong&gt; are critical competencies for professional survival. Technology, work practices and the strategic framework are in a state of constant evolution. The saying that one must keep running even to remain in the same place is more relevant now than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With newer systems, tools and techniques impacting workplace, the risk of obsolescence is indeed high. The only way one can retain employability and skill-criticality is to learn and be a step ahead in the competence ladder. As the ecosystem gets more professionalised, license, certification and skill upgrade can only ensure that you remain ahead of the curve in terms of competence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more employers prefer ready to deploy talent rather than spending time, effort and money on retraining and redeploying talent. While this may still be done for lower-level skills, &lt;strong&gt;for the professional levels, employers prefer expertise off the shelf.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lateral entry is a common practice for middle to senior levels. &lt;em&gt;If you can compete with external resources and prove that you have skills matching and exceeding the alternative resources, then and then only you might be preferred over fresh talent.&lt;/em&gt; There is simply no option but to keep learning and renewing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, more and more &lt;strong&gt;organisations look for executives with internal consulting competence so that they bring in ‘value add’ to the strategies, systems and practices of the organization.&lt;/strong&gt; Sharpening your strategic insights into the industry and company business are critical for your survival and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly,&lt;/em&gt; your &lt;strong&gt;ability and willingness to be a mentor and “go to” expert&lt;/strong&gt; enhance your chances of retention, reward and recognition by the employer. As much as your ability to learn, your enthusiasm and commitment to teach, train and mentor the talent pipeline would be an invaluable asset in your professional repertoire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In the legacy corporate culture, many people believed in and practiced the “irreplaceability” game. They kept knowledge, skills and applications to themselves and somehow led themselves to believe that being “skill critical” would ensure their continuous employment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is yesterday’s survival game and has no place in the digital and transformed corporate culture of today. In fact, being seen as too confidential or reluctant to share and support colleagues might become an albatross around your neck. &lt;strong&gt;From early career, one must develop the ability and confidence to help and mentor others.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do bear in mind that the one sure way to upgrade your own skills is to help someone to acquire and improve them.&lt;/em&gt; Also, corporate working being essentially a team game, your willingness and enthusiasm to be the guide, mentor and hand-holder will earn you immeasurable loyalty and commitment from your team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;fourth&lt;/em&gt; competency that would bolster your career security and resilience is your &lt;strong&gt;professional networking&lt;/strong&gt; extending beyond the immediate work environment. &lt;strong&gt;The power of networking both within and beyond the organization helps you to be current in your functional domain&lt;/strong&gt; and also ensures that in case of need for a career shift, you can access and explore your contacts to tap opportunities. Further, it helps to share industry and technology trends as well as to identify and benchmark ‘best practices’ which can be deployed in your work situation. Maintaining and expanding your professional contacts and keeping your antennae alert to capture emerging trends in your industry and profession can add to your professional value and strategic worth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fifthly, your &lt;strong&gt;emotional resilience and social skills&lt;/strong&gt; are invaluable assets in &lt;strong&gt;crafting your personal brand value&lt;/strong&gt; in your immediate environment as well as within the larger professional domain. There is no substitute for empathy and keeping cool. Emotional regulation skills would help you to see ups, downs, losses and frustrations as inevitable parts of career. &lt;strong&gt;No one can take an insurance against setbacks and even loss of continuity in career; but one can definitely prepare better to get up and get moving from a fall, should that occur.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Practice of Yoga and meditation as well as developing interest in personal pursuits like gardening, painting, writing or travel can enhance your emotional resilience, according to behavioural scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lastly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;one needs to be a realist and accept that change is not only part of career but it is even desirable. It helps us to hone our skills in different contexts and thus adds to our value to prospective employers or even for own entrepreneurial pursuits.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To be financially prepared to take risks of career moves or disruptions is an important aspect of today’s career canvas. One should have &lt;strong&gt;access to liquidity to tide over one year’s living expenses&lt;/strong&gt; plus a buffer for contingencies. This part of personal fund can be deployed in short-term investments including equity, debt funds, fixed deposit and partly in cash too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above is a &lt;strong&gt;blue print of career competency that you should plan and pursue so that you can smartly face the susceptibilities of career graph.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be an early bird and start on your career planning from day one. Use this as an outline and customise or expand the list to suit your needs and aspirations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 30 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/management/behavior/2021/04/30/a-career-survival-guide-for-tough-times.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/management/behavior/2021/04/30/a-career-survival-guide-for-tough-times.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>management</category>
        
        <category>behavior</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Confessions of a Non-Nationalist</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;We were having our sporadic weekend old boys’ meetup, a rare fixture in these days of pandemic. The freewheeling discussions touched upon a range of topics. May be triggered by the prevailing social milieu or in an accidental detour, we stumbled upon an interesting, yet uncomfortable, question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Are you a nationalist?” , asked my effervescent friend. “ Well, I don’t think so,” I replied. “Okay, then you are not patriotic?”, pat came the response.&lt;/em&gt; Though my temptation was to feign inattentiveness in a bid to avoid the futile discussion forward, my spontaneous response was, &lt;strong&gt;“Well, patriotism itself is a bit worn-out idea. Nevertheless, how the hell are you equating nationalism with patriotism?”&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, the discussions took a fast retreat from the alley that would have led to fierce posturing and boisterous arguments. Later that night, as I lay gazing at the emptiness of the enveloping darkness, that evening’s fleeting discussions triggered stray thoughts on the whole issue of virulent nationalism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;What is nationalism, anyway? Is it positive or inherently divisive? Can there be a world beyond nationalism?&lt;/em&gt; These nagging questions are inconvenient and disturbing and so most people conveniently avoid them even in their self-talk.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nationalism as a concept evolved as a result of the &lt;em&gt;search for identity and affiliation&lt;/em&gt; of the early tribal and clannish societies. As they struggled to fend off external invasions and intimidations by others seeking to establish their own moorings and dominance, they defined their version of nationalism in tight terms as if to trap their folks in a tight embrace difficult to untangle .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Historically, as nomads and colonisers gobbled up contiguous geographies for farming, settlement and assertion of brute power, the idea of nationalism took roots in different hues and haze. &lt;strong&gt;Both the invaders and the locals crafted their own notions and folklore around the valour, supremacy and traditions of their kind ‘nationalism.’ The notions of ‘us’ and ‘them’ got accentuated through the reinforcement of nationalism.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is an irony that nationalism which got established as a shield of inclusive identity ended up thriving on a number of corollary ideas of antithesis - exclusion, hostility and intolerance towards diversity. If one looks behind the veil of the superficial unity brought out by the neo-nationalist movements across the world, one would discern icy power struggles and domineering individual assertions for control.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Over the course of evolution of humanity, geographical and lifestyle identities gave way to religion and belief systems as the overarching layer of identity.&lt;/em&gt; While religion intertwined with political nationalism in the pre-liberal era, subsequently religion and statecraft developed a working arrangement of mutual exclusiveness at least in theory. The monarchies which ruled most settlements before the onset of democratic liberalism were quick to sense the utility of religious and ethnic identities as powerful means to divide, insulate and subjugate the masses thereby fending off simmering discontent and anti-incumbency against the regimes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As humanity journeyed into the 19th century and beyond, nationalism of the tribal variety gave way to economic nationalism. The new idea of nationalism based on economic domains was consistent with the outlook of the better educated, diversely skilled and aspirational generations. I believe that &lt;strong&gt;whatever humanity has achieved in terms of physical and social well-being since Industrial Revolution is largely the result of free thinking, openness to see ‘the other’ perspectives and unbridled inquisitiveness.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;More than “Why”, it is “Why not” that has shaped the modern society.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As perspectives broadened and the scope of interactions widened, we saw the blossoming of the age of liberalism. Conservative Right, Liberal Centre and  deviant Left ideology learned to live and let live. Democracy came to be accepted as the more humane, accommodative and acceptable way of governance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;However, the politics of exclusions, privileges and fictitious cultural supremacy still hold sway among a sizeable number of conformists who view change as unnecessary, non-divine and too disturbing.&lt;/strong&gt; Divisive nationalism is fanned by traditionalists across geographies. While ultra-right interests have crept into the political space provided by the liberal democracies,   nations  ruled by autocratic despots, military generals or by puppet regimes propped up by the military encourage and reinforce fierce nationalism founded on exclusion of non-conformists. &lt;em&gt;The continuing stories of threats, devastation and human sufferings in the name of religious, political or pseudo-cultural divisions speak of the hold the psychology of primitive tribalism still has over the presumably modern societies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at history’s catastrophic failures such as Hitler’s Germany, Tsarist Russia or the pre-revolution Chinese Empire – &lt;em&gt;all of them suffered interminably from inflated self-image of cultural supremacy and the myth of infallibility of the ruling dispensation.&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Excessive and impassioned nationalism and pumped-up adulation for the glory of the past spelled disaster, humiliation and demise of many a political dispensation in the long and chequered history of humanity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In contemporary societies, nationalism’s vitriolic divisiveness is still exploited by politicians. Religious nationalism and even sub-regional identity politics based on caste, language and sects come in handy for cunning politicians to carve out and nurture vote banks. &lt;em&gt;Nationalism and the stratification of the same along divisive identities eat into the cohesion of societies and hamper the potential for evolving unifying and secular agenda for development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Today’s world presents immense possibilities for skilling, entrepreneurship  and cross-border commerce on the back of digital connectivity and applications. When the knowledge ecosystem has potential to deliver unprecedented opportunities for upward social and economic mobility, it is indeed an anachronism to allow narrow and restrictive notions of nationalism to apply brakes on progress and prosperity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Nationalism is a psychological aberration, and we owe it to our ancestors, and to our descendants - and to the other species, and to the Earth itself - to move beyond it”, says Steve Taylor of Leeds Beckett University who authored the book ‘The Leap and Spiritual Science’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India’s age-old cultural moorings are on &lt;em&gt;‘vasudhaiva kudumbakam’ (The World is one large family).&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;Developing global perspectives, cultivating inclusiveness and feeling proud about the diversity of our society are critical for our deliverance from the entropy of poverty and mediocrity.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just like nationalism, patriotism too is a two-edged sword. &lt;strong&gt;Patriotism is indeed a very subjective idea that can be conveniently defined and brandished. In most imperfect polities, patriotism is used as a term to count you in as a supporter of the ruling dispensation or rule you out as being against it.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;In a sense, patriotism has restrictive overtones that are anathema to the concept of universal brotherhood.&lt;/em&gt; When the ruling class usurps the moral authority to determine who is patriot and who is not, the concept is extinguished at one go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In my interactions with a number of educated and intelligent youngsters, &lt;em&gt;I am pained to see a creeping willingness to accept, support and propagate politics of hate, exclusion and cultural divisiveness. It is unfortunate and myopic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I would rather be a non-nationalist and a humanist at heart.&lt;/strong&gt; A global citizen at best, who is equally disturbed by a pair of sunken eyes in Africa and by the sight of hungry children struggling to grab a food dole-out in an anonymous Indian city.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 18 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/governance/economics/sociology/2021/04/18/confessions-of-a-non-nationalist.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/governance/economics/sociology/2021/04/18/confessions-of-a-non-nationalist.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>governance</category>
        
        <category>economics</category>
        
        <category>sociology</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The Power of Strategic Compensation </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;C-Suit discussions in India tend to be focussed more on operational items with less of proactive brainstorming on potential opportunities and strategic risks ahead, except in a few corporates with robust management culture and visionary leadership.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even when Boards discuss strategy, the time spent on compensation structure, challenges and strategies is usually far less compared to market, financing and technology/product issues. The availability of options for leveraging executive and employee payments for competitive advantage is relatively less recognized by most corporate leaderships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Payment of wages, salaries and operating incentives are treated as routine – or at best as tactical issue in times of crisis- rather than as strategic priorities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The picture is changing fast now as more and more organizations are waking up to the opportunities for optimising operating cost, enhancing employee engagement and retaining key talent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The size and impact of salary related expenses are too big to be ignored from strategic canvas any more. &lt;em&gt;Salaries and wages accounted for over 30 per cent of factory Gross Value-Add (GVA) in FY 2018-19&lt;/em&gt;&lt;strong&gt;,&lt;/strong&gt; according to the Annual Survey of Industries (ASI) released by the National Statistical Office. In knowledge industry and other sunrise sectors where critical talent commands premium valuation, rewards expenses are significantly higher than in the legacy sectors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Deloitte Report on ‘2021 Global Human Capital Trends’&lt;/strong&gt;, indicates that &lt;em&gt;compensation is the largest component of an organization’s costs&lt;/em&gt;, accounting for &lt;em&gt;as much as 70 percent of total operating costs in some cases&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The context is appropriate for upping the strategic focus on salary elements with the imminent roll out of the new National Wage Code from April 1, 2021.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The new wage code stipulates that basic salary shall be at least 50% of the Cost-to-Company (CTC) remuneration package. This is a major change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Most private employers have been paying relatively lower basic salary for routine jobs for operational reasons including to keep the derived benefits and incidentals pay-out within limits.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The implication of this provision is that the CTC would undergo a rejig in most cases.&lt;/strong&gt; While reducing the existing basic salary component would be too disruptive and lead to widespread dissatisfaction among employees, employers would have to take a hit as a fall out of revising the non-basic component to match the fixed (basic salary) half of the package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;However, the situation provides an opportunity to review, simplify and rationalise the allowances and benefits components, aligning with the statutory guidelines as well as tax provisions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The opportunity can be used to design and dovetail incentives, performance pay and skill-upgrade support&lt;/em&gt; in the overall package so as to make the total package a strategic tool to recognize and reward talent and outcomes generated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would recommend that the strategi troika of &lt;strong&gt;performance-pay, skill-development recognition and key-talent retention&lt;/strong&gt; should be incorporated in the new compensation structure through well-crafted rewards programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the &lt;strong&gt;social security provisions&lt;/strong&gt; such as provident fund and gratuity as well as coverage of employee state insurance (ESI) based medical expenses support, the new code brings in flexibility and enhancement which would go a long way in enabling skill-mobility and end-of-service payments. These provisions would &lt;strong&gt;facilitate ease-of-employment, job changes and exits, all of which have been stifled by the archaic and bureaucratic labour laws and procedures&lt;/strong&gt; which had a “big brother” role for the government in matters of employment contract, termination and payment of salaries and wages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another long pending reform that is part of the new labour code is the &lt;strong&gt;recognition of alternative modes of employment&lt;/strong&gt; such as limited term contracts, outsourced workforce and contract workers. By bringing in transparency and formalisation into the employment framework, the national pool of workforce would gain recognition, security and flexibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is time for us to view employment as a talent-based contract of engagement between employers and workforce which recognizes the freedom and flexibility for both parties to align with changing market conditions while ensuring a robust social security net for workers to support their quest to retain and enlarge employability and skill upgrade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From now on, &lt;strong&gt;companies and executive leaderships should recognize and strategize employee payment as a key element in the long-term health and prosperity of organizations.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, &lt;em&gt;time is ripe even for Governments and the public sector to be proactive on talent management and rewards strategies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lack of outcome-based recognition and rewards programs has been a bane of public sector in most developing nations.&lt;/strong&gt; The return on capital employed in the state-run enterprises has been abysmally low and this has been a major reason for inadequate capital formation in the public domain. Borrowing to meet the payroll expenses and stalling the much-needed investments for system and infrastructure upgrade have proved to be counterproductive in enabling nations to break out of the culture of lethargy and mediocrity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;At the macro level we need to have a compensation policy that pays the socially strategic roles adequately so as to attract people of integrity, talent and commitment to these positions.&lt;/strong&gt; A policeman, school teacher, paramedic, or frontline public servant needs to be paid well and held accountable to generate outcomes that are measurable and challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Such a performance-oriented culture in Government and Public Sector would correct the existing skewness in accountability and rewards management between public sector and private sector. A rationale-based relativity between public and private employment is a must for elevating the entire economy to global standard and to attract talent to both public and private sector with objectivity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, &lt;em&gt;people should have a choice to opt for a career in any of the sectors and should have the flexibility and opportunity to make career shifts laterally or vertically at any stage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That is the sign of a sustainable learning society. That is my dream for India. In realising that dream a national policy on compensation and rewards strategies play a key role.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/economics/governance/2021/03/21/the-power-of-strategic-compensation.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/economics/governance/2021/03/21/the-power-of-strategic-compensation.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>economics</category>
        
        <category>governance</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>It is Time for Tiger and Dragon to Tango!</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Over the past few years, much bad blood has been shed in India-China bilateral relations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before China became the leading factory hub of the world and flooded the global markets with mass merchandise, the Sino-Indian relations that started in the 1950s with an exuberant warmth had soured badly. The unfortunate transgressions of 1962 by the People’s Liberation Army to the utter bewilderment of the ill-prepared Indian troops were just the beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Succession of Chinese regimes under the Communist rule displayed an uncanny knack to exploit the legacy geopolitical fault lines in the sub-continent. The term “all weather friendship” was coined to define China-Pakistan ties mainly to rub salt into the wounded Indian ego rather than out of any long-term love for our Western neighbour. The contributory negligence of ruling dispensations in India and the lack of political bilateralism within the country on strategic neighbourhood relationships have only accentuated the frosty vibes between India and China.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Indian fear of being overrun by the growing clout of the larger neighbour in military might, diplomatic clout and global trade has often led to paranoid responses when stern and gutsy posturing was called for. Much water has flown down Ganges since 1962.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The tactical significance of a working relationship and search for common ground for Indian and Chinese interests have assumed global significance now.&lt;/strong&gt; To be fair to PM Modi, he did bend backwards to please President Xi. But nothing seems to have worked and the Chinese have carried on playing up the regional tensions to their perennial advantage. Their massive economic advantage has allowed them the luxury of using ‘loose purse strings’ to ride rough shod over the vast hinterland of Africa and the less-developed Asia, which are desperately dry of capital for growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The beauty about realpolitik and global diplomatic undercurrents is that these are ever in a state of flux.&lt;/em&gt; The pandemic-induced economic moderation, the creeping realisation that fast-paced Chinese economic expansion of cannot be sustained and the unexpected loss of face that China encountered in their adventurous military moves in the Himalayan valleys have all brought the dragon on to tactical re-posturing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There seems to be a realistic reset of the Chinese aggressiveness.&lt;/strong&gt; I would read this tactical cooling-off reflected by Chinese retreat from its Himalayan adventurism as a window of opportunity that India should grab. We need to iron out the creases and smoothen the relationship with China to a win-win mode .&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I believe that China and India would do well to search for synergies and complementarities in commercial and economic relationship.&lt;/strong&gt; Together these giant economies that are home to over 2.5 billion human beings can be a tremendous force in asserting the Asian prowess. &lt;strong&gt;An India-China economic partnership, if sensitively calibrated can be a gamechanger. It can positively impact much of the global population much beyond both the countries -&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;covering Africa, Middle East, East Asia and Central Asia.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the following reasons, I am all for using the opportunity provided by the tactical retreat of Chinese military from the border areas for giving another chance to peace and progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, &lt;strong&gt;as the world struggles to get back to normalcy post-Covid, India and China need each other in a complementary partnership to spur their domestic growth and renewal.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The combine market is huge in size. Both India and China can gain from collaboration and increased trade.&lt;/em&gt; But to succeed the new paradigm needs to be built up on trust, sharing and long-term perspectives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;India should be able to gain enhanced access to Chinese markets in the sectors in which we hold competitive and strategic advantages- like pharma, IT and value-added commodity intermediaries. Likewise, we need Chinese investment and expertise in infrastructure projects and manufacturing of technology products for the world. &lt;strong&gt;When cooperation can benefit both the economies in terms of huge economic value addition, frittering away the chances for a few political brownie points does not make sense.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secondly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;China has proven expertise in high-tech logistics, manufacturing and construction&lt;/strong&gt; and have implemented many landmark projects in many parts of the world, mostly in Africa, Middle East and developing Asia. We need to leverage the Chinese strengths for fast-tracking our infrastructure upgrade. Keeping China away is like throwing the baby with the bath. If you look at how China built up their competitive position and business depth with the US, they have used tactical agility, accommodation and openness, while keeping their subtle strategic nuances deftly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;There are tremendous opportunities for Indian corporates and Chinese entities to collaborate in building infra projects and participate in the massive privatisation of Public Enterprises.&lt;/strong&gt; Where regulatory framework needs to be redefined, fine-tuned and strengthened to prepare the ground that should be done forthwith.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;China and India seem to be competing fiercely – sometimes not entirely fairly - for strategic ties and commercial contracts in Africa and other developing countries&lt;/strong&gt;; With both Governments implementing confidence building measures, the companies in India and China can benefit and the cost and efficiency of the projects in third countries can greatly improve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourthly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;a positive and constructive relationship between India and China can help the South Asia Region as a whole tremendously.&lt;/strong&gt; For example, to get India and Pakistan to a level of being partners in progress rather than living on perpetual shadow of partition, I strongly believe China – if it can act genuinely in statesman-like role- has a significant role to play a positive role. If China sees genuine and sustainable economic advantages in cooperating with India, they would play a more supportive role in normalising India-Pakistan relations. In fact, Pakistan needs to also think beyond its past bitterness with India because keeping the fires of hate and hurt does not help people or nations to progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifthly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;raising the comfort level with China will smoothen India getting back to Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (RCEP)&lt;/strong&gt; which remains an unfinished agenda without our participation. India being part of RCEP and allaying India’s genuine concerns for ensuring smooth integration into the partnership would be a win-win for China, India and the other ASEAN countries.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Xi and Modi in charge, it looks possible to erase the scars in the relationship and give a fresh start of positive collaboration. China has as much to gain from the massive economic opportunities that India offers as we have opportunities for leveraging China’s capital, expertise and market access. The immediate priority should be to build trust and enhance genuine mutuality. &lt;strong&gt;An assertive Asia can pull not just the immediate neighbourhood, but even Africa and much of the less-developed Middle East from the current economic slump.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I know there would be many naysayers in India who feel comfortable to remain wrapped in the frigidities of the past. An improved relationship with China is definitely a great opportunity for us and much less of a threat. &lt;strong&gt;Considering that we have wasted nearly seven decades in bickering and playing shadow fights, I believe we should give a serious chance to bringing China onboard as a dependable partner in economic and commercial spheres.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/economics/2021/02/19/it-is-time-for-tiger-and-dragon-to-tango.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/economics/2021/02/19/it-is-time-for-tiger-and-dragon-to-tango.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>economics</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is it time up for the conglomerate business model?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“Traditional conglomerates have no future. On average, they are average. And today, average means mediocracy” - Joe Kaeser, CEO of Siemens&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The top ten Indian companies by market capitalisation as of Feb/2021 reads: &lt;em&gt;RIL, TCS, HDFC Bank, Infosys, HUL, HDFC, Kotak Mahindra Bank, SBI, Bajaj Finance and Bharti Airtel.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The list is dominated overwhelmingly by pure-play enterprises rather than business conglomerates.&lt;/strong&gt; We have many legacy industrial houses which have grown haphazardly like wild bushes mostly in the pre-liberalisation years. Many of them accumulated licences/permits and grew into unwieldy behemoths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, &lt;em&gt;it goes to the credit of free market dynamics and the gradual maturing of capital markets in the country that many of them lost out to the newer, nimbler and more focused businesses over time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why is it that large business houses with an assortment of businesses in their portfolio seem less appealing to discerning investors? Some of the key factors for the loss of investor interest in them are rigidity of their corporate structure, power-centric governance processes, blurring of strategic focus and dilution of economic value accretion due to non-synergic businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Globally, the strategic weight of the conglomerate business model has been on the decline. &lt;strong&gt;In the US and in Europe since 1980s, companies have preferred the stand-alone business format to the group structure.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Rise in&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;activism against monopoly practices&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;perception of incremental shareholder value in decoupling of sunrise businesses from the legacy&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;ones&lt;/em&gt; were the key drivers behind this shift. Further, standalone business structure &lt;em&gt;better aligns with the sector-specific interests. Management and regulatory processes are a lot less complex&lt;/em&gt; for standalone enterprises compared to the group entities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;It is time for large business houses to relook at their business model and to take a call on strategic restructuring.&lt;/strong&gt; This is needed to regain the animal spirit that spurred them to expansion in the first place. The context has changed and   new challenges have emerged. &lt;em&gt;Digitalisation opportunities, generational shift in talent and leadership as well as fast-changing competitive landscape&lt;/em&gt; call for &lt;strong&gt;agility, collaboration and customer alignment&lt;/strong&gt; for survival and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Group level consolidation as a model and strategy merits a fresh and objective look. Before we take up a few examples from the contemporary corporate landscape, we need to understand clearly the concept of &lt;em&gt;conglomerate discount.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The enterprise valuation of a conglomerate is done by aggregating the ‘sum-of-parts’ value of individual businesses in the group. &lt;strong&gt;Analysts tend to assign a lesser value to the consolidated business at the group level compared to the sum total of the enterprise values of business verticals.&lt;/strong&gt; Lack of synergy across businesses,  performance lags and cyclical variations  of different businesses result in possible depletion of the overall valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;In this age of super specialisation and digitalisation, small is indeed more beautiful and more effective. Giant corporates tend to be too slow to respond to sudden changes in the business environment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some vital learning points as we review the list of top market cap companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Take the case of ITC.&lt;/em&gt; It has been consistently coming down in the pecking order and has disappeared from the list of 2020. What do you think would have gone wrong when it comes to how the investment community perceives it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Well, ITC’s core business of cigarettes is under perennial regulatory threat&lt;/em&gt; and has serious constraints on future growth potential. However, it has ventured into diverse and unconnected sectors like hospitality where it finds the going tough. &lt;strong&gt;The FMCG business is indeed doing well but in the absence of unlocking through demerger, the massive potential for growth is stymied.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Further, look at Reliance Industries&lt;/em&gt;. In spite of figuring at the top of the table, &lt;em&gt;the sectoral valuation in respect of its Oil and Petrochemicals, Telecom and Retail verticals are at varying stages of maturing and the consolidation at apex level  depresses the aggregate economic value below its potential.&lt;/em&gt;  The slow monetisation of fibre-to-the-home network and  uncertainties regarding 5G are drags on valuation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the short-term till the demerger and listing of Jio platform, the enterprise value is likely to be seen as subdued by the market. The much-hyped possible investment by global Oil majors seems mired in near-term uncertainty too. &lt;em&gt;As of now, RIL to me is like a student with high potential performing below par in exams.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Larsen and Toubro(L&amp;amp;T) offers another perspective in enterprise value unlock.&lt;/em&gt; It has done well to list L&amp;amp;T Infotech (LTI), L&amp;amp;T Tech. Services (LTTS) and L&amp;amp;T Financial Holdings (LTFH) as separate entities. &lt;em&gt;The incremental shareholder value created by these strategic listings is significant&lt;/em&gt;. Look at how the market cap of LTI has soared for example. However, the parent company is still struggling to find its moorings due to the disruptions in order flow and delays in execution pipeline. Any upward mobility in market capitalisation would be in sync with post-Covid recovery of infra spending.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet another example is the consistent accretion to share holder value as well as the road map for future demerger and monetisation of businesses likely in Adani Enterprises.   Their strategy demonstrates a marked preference for pure-play business model post the incubation and curation phase of new businesses.  This would be positive for investor value build-up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do all these examples throw up as lessons for the conglomerates in India?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Firstly, &lt;strong&gt;sticking to core competencies is vital for corporate identity and value creation in an increasingly competitive and connected economy.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Strategy Consulting firms recommend that enterprises with unwieldy and unproductive portfolio should prune their offerings to a viable and critical range. &lt;em&gt;As a thumb rule, if you are not in the top three (or at least top five) players in the sector, it is prudent for you to exit.&lt;/em&gt; This is a pragmatic touchstone for assessing and recalibrating strategies of conglomerates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of how the rush of telecom licence aspirants spoiled the show and burned their pockets when India liberalised telecom sector will ever remain as a rude reminder of the dangers of crony capitalism and investment adventurism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The strategic focus  of Tata Group on reinforcing the verticals and enabling the growth of independent businesses needs to be commended.&lt;/em&gt; Having inducted youthful leaderships and cleaned up the strategy and processes, the group seems to have enabled standalone companies to pursue market dominance and execution excellence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secondly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;the strategic need for conglomerates today is to leverage technology, talent and leadership to capitalise on the emerging  opportunities for growth.&lt;/strong&gt;  Digital transformation is critical to the evolution of conglomerates into a few robust pure-play businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The age of the big and overbearing conglomerates is over. Now is the time for compact, focused and agile corporations.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 07 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/management/2021/02/07/is-it-time-up-for-the-conglomerate-business-model.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/management/2021/02/07/is-it-time-up-for-the-conglomerate-business-model.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>management</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Republic Day Musings -Reimagining Nationalism </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;This year India celebrates a subdued Republic Day with scaled down pageantry and shortened marching route along the Rajpath. A fallout of pandemic induced restraint.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of late, a lot of talk and tangential debates have been circulating on the concepts of Nationalism and Patriotism. As the Republic turns seventy-one, it is appropriate to look dispassionately at the narratives around these ideas. The fledgling Republic set sail in 1950 on the experiment of representative governance on a scale never before witnessed by the world. Many doubts and apprehensions were raised on the efficacy of democratic governance in a grossly illiterate and economically deprived society which was fragmented by age-old casteist fault-lines and ravaged by violent communal carnage in the aftermath of partition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite massive under-accomplishment in terms of human development, as we look back at the years gone by, there are reasons to feel pride and satisfaction at the strides made in many aspects of the economy. &lt;strong&gt;Achieving food security and raising significant share of the population above sustenance level are indeed creditable.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;However deep down in the psyche of the nation lie the uneasy embers of how we understand and relate to the concepts of nationalism and patriotism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What is nationalism? In an absurd simplification, some people attempt to define it in terms of majoritarianism.&lt;/strong&gt; Those who do fail to appreciate the complexity of how majoritarian connotations can skew the lofty ideals of nationalism or patriotism. Both these concepts would be devoid of vitality and spirit if the vast sections of marginalised population do not feel passion about them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One need not go far, but just look across the border to see how majoritarian assertion can reduce minority mindset, confidence and self-belief to tatters. Where did the sizeable number of minorities who opted to stay back in cities like Karachi and Lahore disappear?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Surely, our Republic was not meant to acquiesce the attempts of numerical majority to trample the diversity and localised sensibilities of the grass-root societies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Let us have the courage of conviction to admit that there have been and still are sporadic attempts to erect walls of majoritarian cultural fortification.&lt;/strong&gt; Such elements in the population are often emboldened by the illusion of passive support of the ruling dispensation. &lt;em&gt;Look at the storming of the Capitol Hill by right-wing White supremacist recently.&lt;/em&gt; If so brazen an intrusion can take place in the citadel of American democracy, such aberration can indeed happen elsewhere too - if the culture of hate and exclusion is tolerated, let alone encouraged. &lt;em&gt;There are many lessons democracies can learn from the fall of Trump.&lt;/em&gt; Democracy as an institution needs a benign and benevolent approach to weaker and differing viewpoints. There is simply no place for riding roughshod over dissent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This Republic Day, let us not be blind to the lurking dangers of overreach by extremist ideologies on either side of the political spectrum.&lt;/strong&gt; The maturity of a democracy is in its ability to tolerate and be concerned about the other view point. &lt;em&gt;I for one feel proud as an Indian that the protesting farmers can have a tractor march in Delhi on the same day, we have the ceremonial armed forces Parade.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patriotism&lt;/strong&gt; has outlived its narrow geographical meaning and has transcended to a truly ‘&lt;em&gt;vasudhaiva kudumbakam’ (the world as a family) outlook&lt;/em&gt; over the years. In the olden days most people used to live in or around their native village. They used to work in their family holding and shared the fruits of labour as a common possession. In the agrarian and feudalistic societies, family feuds and revenge fights were common. For survival, aggressive repulsion of the “outsiders” was more of a necessity. Gone are those days. &lt;strong&gt;Today, people travel far and wide and many people earn their livelihood in places far away from their roots.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;One is often a ‘pravasi’ (emigrant) either in own country or abroad.&lt;/em&gt; Naturally, the intense loyalty and sense of belonging to the place of birth or the immediate society where one grew up have diluted considerably. &lt;strong&gt;People do develop affinity, comfort and even a sense of longing for the new found sanctuary of security, financial self-reliance and the behavioural congruence to the new cultural environment.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Patriotism is today more of a behavioural expression of&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;esprit de corps&lt;/em&gt; (mix of belongingness and loyalty) &lt;strong&gt;and spontaneity is the characteristic of patriotism.&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;Any attempt to curate patriotism through targeted interventions would actually create a tendency to rebel or at least be indifferent&lt;/em&gt;. That is why the regimentation of a communist or autocratic society does not gel with a liberal democracy spirit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Further, &lt;em&gt;in a truly inclusive liberal democracy patriotism can’t have sponsors and patrons. No place for moral policing to enforce patriotism.&lt;/em&gt; The challenge of nation building in a liberal democracy is to create a climate of care, compassion and facilitation. It makes most people to see, feel and internalise a spontaneous feeling of belongingness and mutuality of interests. &lt;strong&gt;Education, parenting and peer relations are the foundations of positive nation building.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Nationalism and patriotism are therefore more of soft competencies that would get reinforced through positive behavioural outcomes of the social learning.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us therefore use the occasion of this unique Republic Day in the tapering phase of lockdown period to &lt;strong&gt;introspect whether by acts or omissions we have helped ourselves and our families and friends to be more accommodative, open and caring.&lt;/strong&gt; If we allowed ourselves to be pawns in the manipulative chess game of wily politicians who benefit by playing up one against the other, it is time to regain our conscience and the right for free thinking and rising above walls of fragmentation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spontaneity, positivism, appreciation of diversity and respect for the right of another person to be different are the qualities that would make us worthy citizens of a liberal democracy. &lt;strong&gt;A simple but valuable rededication to define nationalism and patriotism in broader and accretive manner is the need of the hour.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy Republic Day Greetings!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/governance/2021/01/25/republic-day-musings-reimagining-nationalism.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/governance/2021/01/25/republic-day-musings-reimagining-nationalism.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>governance</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>നവകേരള വിഹായസ് : സ്വതന്ത്ര ചിന്തയും തുറന്ന സംവാദവും</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;ദളം 1; 19   ജനുവരി 2021&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;പക്ഷം പിടിക്കാതെയുള്ള രാഷ്ട്രീയ അവബോധം ഒരു പക്വതയുള്ള ജനാധിപത്യ സമൂഹത്തിൻറെ മുഖമുദ്രയാണ്.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;പോഷക സംഘടനകളിലൂടെ ചെറുപ്രായംമുതലേ ബൗദ്ധിക അടിമത്തം ഊട്ടിയുറപ്പിക്കാൻ പാർട്ടികൾ തത്രപ്പാട് നടത്തുകയും വിജയിക്കുകയും ചെയ്യുന്ന നമ്മുടെ നാട്ടിൽ സ്വതന്ത്ര രാഷ്ട്രീയ ബോധം നിരുത്സാഹപ്പെടുത്തപ്പെടുന്നു.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;പക്ഷവും സമുദായവും മുഖവും നോക്കാതെ ഇന്ഡ്യയെ മൊത്തം ഒന്നായികാണാൻ എന്നാണ് പുതു തലമുറയെങ്കിലും തയാറാകുന്നത്?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ഇനിയും മനസ്സാക്ഷിയെ പ്രസ്ഥാനങ്ങൾക്കും സങ്കുചിതയ്ക്കും അടിയറ വെയ്ക്കാത്തവർക്കു ചിന്തിക്കാൻ സമയമായി.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/19/%E0%B4%A8%E0%B4%B5%E0%B4%95%E0%B5%87%E0%B4%B0%E0%B4%B3-%E0%B4%B5%E0%B4%BF%E0%B4%B9%E0%B4%BE%E0%B4%AF%E0%B4%B8-%E0%B4%B8-%E0%B4%B5%E0%B4%A4%E0%B4%A8-%E0%B4%A4-%E0%B4%B0-%E0%B4%9A%E0%B4%BF%E0%B4%A8-%E0%B4%A4%E0%B4%AF%E0%B5%81%E0%B4%82-%E0%B4%A4%E0%B5%81%E0%B4%B1%E0%B4%A8-%E0%B4%A8-%E0%B4%B8%E0%B4%82%E0%B4%B5%E0%B4%BE%E0%B4%A6%E0%B4%B5%E0%B5%81%E0%B4%82.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/2021/01/19/%E0%B4%A8%E0%B4%B5%E0%B4%95%E0%B5%87%E0%B4%B0%E0%B4%B3-%E0%B4%B5%E0%B4%BF%E0%B4%B9%E0%B4%BE%E0%B4%AF%E0%B4%B8-%E0%B4%B8-%E0%B4%B5%E0%B4%A4%E0%B4%A8-%E0%B4%A4-%E0%B4%B0-%E0%B4%9A%E0%B4%BF%E0%B4%A8-%E0%B4%A4%E0%B4%AF%E0%B5%81%E0%B4%82-%E0%B4%A4%E0%B5%81%E0%B4%B1%E0%B4%A8-%E0%B4%A8-%E0%B4%B8%E0%B4%82%E0%B4%B5%E0%B4%BE%E0%B4%A6%E0%B4%B5%E0%B5%81%E0%B4%82.html</guid>
        
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How prepared is India for economic recovery agenda? </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is said that going downhill is easy, but climbing back is quite an effort. It is true of nations and economies as much as for individuals. Downward journey is hardly voluntary. We do not plan to go downhill, aspirations are always to climb up the ladder of competence, wealth and influence. However, regression on progress and prosperity does happen due to emergence of risks for which we are not prepared. Covid pandemic has produced one such inflection point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How nations prepare themselves for the strenuous haul back to normalcy and advancement would determine the new pecking order post the pandemic. World Economic Forum(WEF), the Davos (Switzerland)-based think tank of global though-leaders and strategists has come out with a special edition of Global Competitiveness Report in the beginning of 2021 focusing on &lt;strong&gt;“How Countries are Performing on the Road to Recovery”.&lt;/strong&gt; The Report provides an insightful agenda and ominous status-check on the preparedness of nations for recovery and growth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is especially relevant to look at how India fares among the comity of nations in the scramble to get ready for the post-Covid challenges and opportunities. For precisely three reasons, India’s state of preparedness attracts critical examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;the wider world, especially the liberal democracies and multilateral funding and development institutions expect India to emerge as a counter-weight to China&lt;/strong&gt;’s aggressive push to be the leading economy of the world. They are eager to see whether India can indeed measure up to the task and that too within the near to medium term.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secondly,&lt;/em&gt; the PM and Government have upped the narrative of an aspirational India aiming to become a USD 5 Trillion economy in the next few year. Though the call for &lt;em&gt;Atmnirbhar Bharat&lt;/em&gt; does sound a jaded formula that fitted more appropriately to the ecosystem of 1960sor 70s, &lt;strong&gt;there are many people who would like to disregard the semantics and look for substance, strategy and commitment on the part of Government to leap at the ambitious target.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly,&lt;/em&gt; there are indeed supporting factors like &lt;strong&gt;demographic advantage of a young workforce, a varied and experienced corporate mix spanning a range of traditional and emerging business domains and a geopolitical environment that is much more favourably inclined to Indian role&lt;/strong&gt; and collaboration than at any time in the past. &lt;em&gt;The challenge for India is to diplomatically manoeuvre Chinese machinations with tact, restraint and accommodation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this benign context and in the wake of immense possibilities, what is the story on the ground? &lt;em&gt;Are we in the game of upping our global competitiveness with the seriousness, focus and commitment that the situation demands?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The latest WFM Report specially focuses on “&lt;em&gt;the priorities and policies needed to reboot economic systems in the longer run&lt;/em&gt; to achieve sustainable and inclusive prosperity over the next 3-5 years”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Report talks about lessons for Governments from the Covid experience. Essentially, going forward &lt;strong&gt;nations need to reboot governance with strategic depth and long-term orientation&lt;/strong&gt; so that not only do economies recover fast but also build resilience to meet similar contingencies that could arise in future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More and more nations would zero-in on a focussed agenda for economic recovery resting on &lt;strong&gt;five pillars&lt;/strong&gt; - Health Services upgrade, comprehensive Skill Development covering public and private sectors, Digitalisation of public service delivery and incentivisation of digital transformation of economy, Leveraging Globalisation advantages with national development priorities as well as Structural and Governance Process Reforms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us look at how India fares against these agenda items and what lies ahead in terms of opportunities and challenges for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;Public Health Services have unfortunately not got the required attention in India’s governance and budgetary allocations over the years.&lt;/strong&gt; Health Infrastructure build-up, quality of service delivery and process enhancements suffered due partly to the lopsided structure of Centre-State power sharing envisaged by the Constitution. Till very recently, federal spending on boosting health infrastructure has been minimal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the absence of adequate and efficient public spending and infrastructure upgrade, the health services delivery pipeline got skewed in favour of private investment.&lt;/em&gt; The lack of balance between public and private health care facilities meant that the public had to take recourse to costly private health care for want of alternative. &lt;em&gt;When healthcare become captive to affordability, the general health index suffers badly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meanwhile, the public health administration in most states got mired in a culture of graft, leakages and nepotism, traits reinforced through decades of governance slackness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time has come to rejig the strategic focus on universal public health services, the most vital pillars of human development. Spending on Health as a percentage of GDP needs to quadruple both at Centre and States&lt;/strong&gt; – more so for those States low down in the pecking order on these counts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The second&lt;/em&gt; priority area is &lt;strong&gt;Comprehensive Skill Development&lt;/strong&gt;. The WEF Report says that &lt;em&gt;among the G-20 nations, India fares the worst in terms of skill-set adequacy to meet the post Covid economic opportunities and challenges.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among school educated and university graduate categories, &lt;strong&gt;India’s score on skill adequacy deteriorated by nearly 25% during the period 2016-2020 as against a gain of 10 to 15% recorded over the same period by China and South Korea.&lt;/strong&gt; Lack of focus, commitment and collaboration across the federal spectrum could be the reasons for this state of affairs. In India, the gap between political rhetoric and ground realities has been the most pronounced in this vital aspect of development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;If we have to gain global manufacturing competitiveness, national skill development strategies, plans and programs need urgent and holistic upgrade.&lt;/strong&gt; Academic-Industry-Government triad has to work in sync on mission mode to prepare the talent readiness. &lt;strong&gt;Real and meaningful monetary and tax incentivisation of organized sector for skill development in both fresh and experience categories should be considered as a policy initiative.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;we need to align the idea of &lt;em&gt;Atmnirbhar Bharat&lt;/em&gt; to the strategic need to leverage global alliances, partnerships and trade relations.&lt;/strong&gt; If &lt;em&gt;Atmnirbhar&lt;/em&gt; means competence advancement and collaboration building to attract emerging technologies, capital inflows and global supply-chain linkages, it would help scale up our commercial and economic clout. But &lt;strong&gt;if we fall prey to the temptations of protective insulation of our economy, the result would be regressive in the long term.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When pushed beyond a point, aggressive nationalism can do more harm than good.&lt;/em&gt; Look at how Trump’s &lt;em&gt;Make America Great Again&lt;/em&gt; campaign in fact reduced America’s global positioning and influence drastically over a span of just four years. &lt;strong&gt;It is time for us to define ‘&lt;em&gt;Atmnirbhar’ as&lt;/em&gt; a positive and inviting global proposition by India opening up for capital, technology, talent and trade.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourthly,&lt;/em&gt; digitalisation did indeed become the saviour in limiting the impact of the sudden lockdowns and immobility. The WEF Report states emphatically that &lt;strong&gt;governments which had built out the digital delivery of public services were much better placed to disburse emergency funding to distressed companies and households.&lt;/strong&gt; In India, digital technology enabled direct transfer of benefits and cash support to millions of needy households affected by loss of jobs and reverse migration. Can you imagine what a mess it would have been without the &lt;em&gt;Jan Dhan&lt;/em&gt; Accounts and digitally beefed-up public distribution network? &lt;strong&gt;We need to fast-track the digitalisation of public service delivery to expand its reach, coverage, variety and efficiency. 5-G rollout to be fast-tracked is therefore a key priority for the nation.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifthly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;reforms need to be speeded up to bring in transparency, eliminate scope for personal discretion and nepotism as well as to plug loopholes for leakage of public money.&lt;/strong&gt; Tremendous progress has been achieved by some States in digital delivery of public services. This needs to be the national agenda and should break the barriers of entitlement and privileges of the better endowed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vaccine Rollout has started and hopefully would go through with the least glitches. Economic activities have started looking up. May be in a year’s time, unless there is a threat from a mutant virus, the Covid interregnum would pass as a nightmare that struck humanity hard and sudden. But &lt;strong&gt;the lessons from the past year would have hopefully changed the global perception of risk and ability to respond with agility to crises for ever.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Afterall, at the end of the pain and loss of yesterday, the serene and refreshing dawn would herald a more optimistic future for humanity. Hopefully, a better prepared India would be in a stronger position to take emerging economic challenges head on.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/economics/2021/01/17/how-prepared-is-india-for-economic-recovery-agenda.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/economics/2021/01/17/how-prepared-is-india-for-economic-recovery-agenda.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>economics</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is Equity investment Your Cup of Tea?</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Indian Stock Market recovered from the lows of March 2020 to touch record highs even as the economy faced unprecedented disruptions – widespread lockdown, slump in business and jobs, operational uncertainties, bankruptcies and mounting debt. It may sound ironic that despite the gloom and uncertainties around, the benchmark NIFTY Index of National Stock Exchange zoomed past 14500 and the counterpart BSE Sensex (of Bombay Stock Exchange) has gone past 49,000 . Sensex would ascend Mount 50 K possibly around Budget time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Amidst the fireworks in the bourses and celebrations by Foreign Portfolio Investors and High Networth Individuals, most Indians have remained silent spectators on the side-lines. With a retail participation rate below 2% of the population at around 20 Million individual investors, substantial majority of Indians avoid investing their money in equity markets.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;True, over the past few months, possibly due to slackness in professional and business activities in the wake of lockdown, many young and first-time investors have ventured into online equity trading. Number of fresh dmat accounts opened has significantly increased. Yet the number of sceptics continue to be high. &lt;strong&gt;What is it that hinders even sections of population with affordability and the advantages of age and saving potential from taking to equity investment?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Typically, the population can be roughly divided into three broad slices on the propensity for equity investment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;small segment of natural investors&lt;/strong&gt; forming around 2-5 percent with high net-worth, traditional business orientation and risk resilience takes to investing like duck to water.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the other end of the spectrum, typically around 25-30 percent of people struggle for day-to-day survival. This group has neither deployable savings nor risk-taking ability to take up equity investment. This segment of people at the borderline sustenance level could be as high as 50 percent of the population in the aftermath of the lockdown economic pressures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then there is &lt;strong&gt;the bulky middle segment&lt;/strong&gt; which comprises mainly of professionals, first generation employees, small and medium entrepreneurs and gig workers. &lt;em&gt;Mostly young, educated, digitally enabled and ambitious, these are usually the trend setters and influencers in a market economy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of equity investment behaviours, this critical middle segment is the most natural group with potential to migrate to the retail equity investor category. If retail participation in equity has to improve this segment has to gain competence and confidence to engage actively in capital market activities. By being on the side-lines, this potential group of prospective investors do miss out on the opportunities to take advantage of the action in the bourse. Afterall, it isn’t rocket science to make money in the stock market!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Equity investment like any other financial decision-making is a trade-off between risks and rewards. How you perceive, assess and leverage these two factors to generate returns is essentially a behavioural process.&lt;/em&gt; You can train yourself to be good at that just like you could pick up driving or swimming skills by practice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Successful equity market investment is a function of Awareness, Analysis and Behaviours.&lt;/strong&gt; I would suggest the skill-mix for sustainable equity investment would be essentially three factors - &lt;em&gt;knowledge of economy and business, data analysis and interpretation skills and emotional and behavioural resilience.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to be an informed investor. &lt;strong&gt;Awareness&lt;/strong&gt; is the foundation for equity investment competence and would cover a wide range of economic, industry and corporate knowledge. One has to know the broader macro-economic realities, trends and the likely opportunities and challenges. Equally important is the awareness about legal, tax and procedural framework.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While one can always depend on advisers and brokerages for guidance, I believe it is important to do extensive self-study and be prepared to take cautious, calm and step-by-step approach to investment. Making a habit of reading a financial newspaper would help you to stay upto-date on current and emerging business and economic trends. Plenty of resources are available over the internet and media channels on business finance and economic trends. However, one should be wary of prescriptive guidance since motivated opinions can lead you to blind alleys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us to the second success factor for equity investment- Analysis. A basic knowledge of &lt;strong&gt;financial and technical analysis&lt;/strong&gt; would boost your ability to identify opportunities to spot potential stock picks for upside.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Financial analysis&lt;/em&gt; looks at key financial performance indicators of the company such as Profit and Loss Account and Balance Sheet of Companies. This would help to broadly assess the financial health of the underlying business. Basic skills to read and interpret financial statements can be acquired without much technicalities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While financial analysis helps you to understand the intrinsic value and growth trend of the business, technical analysis&lt;/em&gt; deals with analysing and interpreting the stock price movement in the market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Observing the stock price movements during the day, week, month, quarter and year could give insight into investor perceptions and confidence in the potential value of the share. When we buy shares of a company, the price we pay reflect the current perceived value of the future earnings potential of the business.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ability to interpret chart patterns would be helpful in identifying and aligning with market movement. Fundamentally business performance, the uniqueness and market potential of the product and services portfolio of the company and the quality of its management are the key determinants for you to zero in on likely ‘winner’ stocks. I would say technical analysis is secondary to fundamental financial strength of the company.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without going much into technicalities of chart patterns, the Price to Earning (P/E) ratio of the stock over time as well as against peer group would help in making trading and investment decisions. With all these inputs, one can get an approximate 360-degree perspective of the scrip. But any analysis is relevant at the time of making the assessment since any of the external or internal factors impacting the performance of the company would possibly change over time. Hence the need for continuous review and monitoring of your portfolio.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stock Market often witnesses manipulative moves by companies and investors trying to create uptrends or downslides to gain from such moves. Everyone doesn’t play by the rule. &lt;strong&gt;Hence going by price movements without due weight on business fundamentals can mislead you into investing in the wrong stocks.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Securities and Exchange Board of India (SEBI) has over the years brought in many regulatory guidelines and procedural upgrades for enhancing transparency and accountability and punishing malafide operators. There is still need for caution. It is your money and you need to be alert and alive to ground situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;third&lt;/em&gt; and most important competence for successful investment is your &lt;strong&gt;emotional resilience&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;. Patience, consistency, alertness and self-belief&lt;/em&gt; are key behavioural traits for being an equity investor.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me close on a personal note. I took to investment in equity around two decades back. Based on my experience I would suggest &lt;strong&gt;five golden rules for those who are interested but hesitant to take the plunge.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, &lt;em&gt;it is never late to start.&lt;/em&gt; The equity market in India has been attracting massive global and domestic investor interest. The depth and breadth of our market are expanding. &lt;em&gt;Better late than never, make an entry and take baby steps to find your moorings.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secondly, consistency, continuity and confidence would help you to build your portfolio over time.&lt;/em&gt; There will surely be ups and downs. A slow and systematic investor can grow his portfolio irrespective of market swings. It is important to have the mindset of a marathon runner and not a sprinter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly, never make the mistake of borrowing to invest in equity market.&lt;/em&gt; If you want sustainable equity investment, do deploy only that part of your savings that you can park for a medium to long term comfortably. As a thumb rule, it is wise not to exceed 20% of your disposable savings in equity investment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fourthly, I suggest that you follow a two-basket strategy for equity investment.&lt;/em&gt; Identify a core portfolio of handful of stocks for value investment where you perceive potential for medium to long term growth. You should research and identify a select few businesses and corporates that you are passionately convinced about long term prospects. You can have a &lt;em&gt;second bucket for pure- play trading&lt;/em&gt; where you can look at making short term money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Finally, train your mind to be objective, resilient and willing to handle setbacks&lt;/em&gt; and challenges dispassionately. Most people burn their fingers in the bourse because they allow themselves to be driven by what Allen Greenspan called “irrational exuberance”. To know when to exit and when to stay quiet are as much important as going long on stocks. Emotional Intelligence is perhaps the most important competency for being a sustainable investor.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/behavior/economics/2021/01/12/is-equity-investment-your-cup-of-tea.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/behavior/economics/2021/01/12/is-equity-investment-your-cup-of-tea.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>behavior</category>
        
        <category>economics</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>How Well Are You Managing Your Personal Finances? </title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;It is New Year time, yet again. The year that has just gone by turned out to be unlike any in the recent memory. Providing unprecedented perspectives. Replete with lessons for future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two key lessons most of us learned the hard way in 2020 related to our work routines and our comfort level with personal finances. Both got disrupted unimaginably. As for work, home and office have twinned themselves into a seamless continuum. A new regimen of remote working, virtual consultation and self-supervision has settled reasonably well for most of us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most of us adjusted to the &lt;em&gt;Work from Home&lt;/em&gt; mindset, coping with the risks to personal finance stability has emerged as a bigger challenge. &lt;strong&gt;Inadequacies in basic financial capabilities and the culture of taking things for granted have hardly helped us when faced with the unexpected crisis.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Too many of us, especially young professionals, have grown accustomed to thinking of job losses, missed loan payments or cuts and deferments in salary as belonging to another world. Possibly a world of fiction from the wild West.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Time has come to look at personal finance competence as a critical success factor for career and life.&lt;/strong&gt; Millennials, professionals, entrepreneurs and homemakers have all faced the blunt of the financial disruptions in the past year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take the case of Sangeetha, a twenty something digital geek. She was on cloud nine when at the end of a high-pressure placement session, the prospective employer, a global leader in digital technologies, handed over her Offer Letter. For all her self-assurance, she was simply bowled over by the all-important part of the letter, the package offered. – annual CTC of Rupees 60 Lakhs. Three years down the line, the Covid disruptions shook the comfort level of her income pipeline with an across-the -board cut in salaries. The bulge on her credit card spending – a full threesome all loaded up – began to bite. Her bank started pestering for the accumulating dues against her hefty housing loan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perhaps for the first time since taking up the cushy job, she felt insecure in terms of finances. Borrowing money from friends or parents had not crossed her mind till then. She couldn’t help thinking aloud, &lt;em&gt;“I wish I had been little less reckless with my spending!”&lt;/em&gt; Many millennials and young professionals have become compulsive shoppers and reckless spenders on the back of easy liquidity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Financial planning and ability to manage cashflows are basic life skills critical for survival, peace of mind and security&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;Yet, this all-important competency is hardly ever taught in schools and colleges.&lt;/strong&gt; For most of us, personal finance habits have been picked up on the go. Unplanned and haphazard, they have evolved over the years like unwieldy bushes growing by the way side.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do we understand by a &lt;em&gt;competency&lt;/em&gt;? It is more than just awareness or techniques. &lt;strong&gt;It is the behavioural manifestation of an ability that becomes second nature to us&lt;/strong&gt;. Like swimming, driving or learning, managing own finance is something that we need to train ourselves for.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the competency model suggested by the &lt;em&gt;Pennsylvania State University Sokolov-Miller Family Financial and Life Skills Centre&lt;/em&gt;, the comprehensive personal finance skill-set comprises of five core competencies - &lt;strong&gt;Earning, Saving &amp;amp; Investing, Spending, Borrowing&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;Protecting.&lt;/strong&gt; Each of these aspects of managing our income and wealth has potential to make or mar our long-term wellness and positive orientation towards life. Yet many of us are guilty of indifference towards handling our own finances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we stare at the New Year with its share of possible uncertainties and challenges, it is appropriate to make a few simple and easy to follow resolutions on our personal finance skills. If you have been negligent or careless so far, the jolt of &lt;strong&gt;the pandemic lockdown and its fallouts would have alerted you to the pitfalls of not planning, monitoring, reviewing and improving your income, savings, spending and risk management behaviours&lt;/strong&gt;. If you have been managing your money matters systematically and to a plan, you have nevertheless an opportunity to enhance your capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would suggest you six action points on your personal financial competence. Needless to say, these are generic observations and you need to customise your plan based on your perceptions and commitments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Firstly&lt;/em&gt;, one must &lt;strong&gt;review own “as is” personal finance situation&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Every individual, in terms of finances, is similar to a business enterprise. Your income, expenses, savings, investments and risk management need comprehensive understanding and constant review.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You need to review the documents such as your tax filing, bank statements, credit/debit card transactions, savings, investments and insurance actions for the past year. This will give you insights into the major income, expense, asset and liability build-up during the year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Secondly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;one needs to make a draft financial plan for the coming year&lt;/strong&gt; taking key inputs from the critical examination of your log for the past year and adding, modifying or eliminating the items based on priorities and risk perception. Through an iterative review, you can refine your plan. Convert your plan into a budget statement broken down to monthly details. It is important to take the budgeting and follow-up as a serious exercise in financial self-discipline.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Thirdly,&lt;/em&gt; managing expenses prudently is a habit that needs conscious efforts to develop. While earnings follow a relatively stable and steady pattern in normal times, spending is susceptible to our behavioural discipline. &lt;em&gt;Lack of caution and moderation in availing of loans, using credit or debit cards or committing to speculative investments have led many people down the path of self-destruction.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Early habits of prudent spending, systematic savings and planned long term investments would risk-proof your mid-career and later years.&lt;/strong&gt; As a thumb rule, in your twenties and thirties, you should systematically save at least 30 to 40 percent of your income. As you go into your middle age, expenses for children’s education and even medical expenses would increase. So, savings would probably get moderated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indiscreet spending in early years of career not only reduces financial resilience in later years but also induces development of bad personal finance habits. It becomes difficult to get back to financial discipline once you are used to slackness in controlling expenses. The inability to regulate the urge to over-spend, over-shop or flaunt affluence levies a high price on the later years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With technology changes happening with lightning speed and with business models evolving continuously, the possibilities of redundancies, job losses and involuntary career shifts can no longer be dismissed. Hence financially one should be prepared to take the hit if and when it comes. Enough cushion should be built in to support a year or two without earnings. Similarly, if you happen to bite the bullet to be an entrepreneur at a later date, there should be financial ability to manage with little business income for the initial years. &lt;em&gt;It is here that your savings and investment habits would need to be realistic and flexible.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This brings us to the fourth area of personal finance- investments&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;strong&gt;It is necessary to build a diverse, liquid and productive portfolio of investments early on in your career.&lt;/strong&gt; As the saying goes, never put all your eggs in one basket. It is critical to diversify your investment portfolio and align your investment mix to your risk profile with respect your age, commitments and earnings curve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asset allocation within your investment basket has to be continuously reviewed and adjusted. &lt;strong&gt;Many people make the mistake of building unwieldy portfolio of investment and then leaving it unattended for years. They discover later on to their utter frustration that the value of investments has eroded irretrievably.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An uncared investment is like an untended garden. Left unattended, the garden degrades into a mess of unwieldy bushes and weeds. One lesson I learned the hard way is that unless you have interest, time and commitment to monitor, review, churn and prune your investment basket, it is better not to be an investor at all. &lt;em&gt;Every rupee invested is your hard-earned money and it is irresponsible to do investments without passion and commitment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Fifthly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;tax planning competence is an integral part of financial literacy. The tax implications of your income, investments and savings should be well understood.&lt;/strong&gt; A review session with your Chartered Accountant should be scheduled and conducted at least twice a year – mid and end of the year. Basic competence on Income Tax laws and rules would help you not only for compliance, but also to ensure that you take advantage of provisions for tax benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sixthly,&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt;it is important to look at the risk resilience of your personal finances periodically.&lt;/strong&gt; This would cover not only how you secure your investments but also how you prepare yourself to meet contingencies that may arise in your career or business. &lt;strong&gt;Awareness of exit routes and flexibilities are as equally important as the entry and sustenance of investment and wealth management.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While wishing all readers a happy and prosperous New Year, I do hope that &lt;em&gt;in the coming year most of us would be better informed, prudent, confident and well prepared in managing our personal finances.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0530</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/economics/behavior/2020/12/30/how-well-are-you-managing-your-personal-finances.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/economics/behavior/2020/12/30/how-well-are-you-managing-your-personal-finances.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>economics</category>
        
        <category>behavior</category>
        
        <category></category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
